<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ansvvere to a letter of a Iesuited gentleman, by his cosin, Maister A.C. Concerning the appeale; state, Iesuits</title>
            <author>Copley, Anthony, 1567-1607?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1601</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 206 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12204</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5735</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108680</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844337</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844337</idno>
            <idno type="VID">178002</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12204)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178002)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1345:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ansvvere to a letter of a Iesuited gentleman, by his cosin, Maister A.C. Concerning the appeale; state, Iesuits</title>
                  <author>Copley, Anthony, 1567-1607?</author>
                  <author>Champney, Anthony, 1569?-1643?, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>80, 79-122 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Newly imprinted [by Felix Kingston],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1601.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A.C. = Anthony Copley.</note>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Anthony Champney.</note>
                  <note>Concerning the appeal against the Archpriest George Blackwell.</note>
                  <note>The words "appeale; state, Iesuits." are bracketed together on the title page.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Quires E-P have vertical chain lines.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jesuits --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:178002:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:178002:1"/>
            <p>AN ANSWERE TO A LETTER OF A IESVITED GENTLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, by his Coſin, Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>A.C.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the
<list>
                  <item>APPEALE;</item>
                  <item>STATE,</item>
                  <item>IESVITS.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Recta Securus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Newly Imprinted. 1601.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:178002:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:178002:2"/>
            <head>An anſwere to a Letter of a <hi>Ieſuited Gentleman.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Coſin; I haue receiued your letter of the firſt of this preſent, writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a ſpirit too derogatiue from the honors and innocence of the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealant-Prieſts, &amp; ſuperero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue in the praiſe of Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its, as it were aboue Ieſus. Wherein you ſhew your ſelfe vncharitable in the one, immoderate in the other, vncatholicke in each. But perhaps you holde your ſelfe herein excuſable, as being ſo affected either in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and reuerence to, and of your ghoſtly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (who happily is a Ieſuit) or in reſpect you are willing to runne with the greater number. If the firſt, take it with you that the Ieſuits in this caſe of the Appeale, are Principals on the one partie, &amp; ſo in iuſtice to be thought partiall: if the other, what ſo erres as the moſt? You are (good Couſin) to captiue your ſences rather to the <hi>ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,</hi> then to the Number of any obiect, and ſo farre forth to iudge your ſelfe in the right or wrong, as you apprehend the ſame right or wrong: and to runne with the moſt (making that your ground)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:178002:3"/> is very vulgar. True it is, that to erre with autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is leſſe ſhame, though no leſſe blame, and therefore your better excuſe may bee vpon Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Arch-prieſt; which notwithſtanding is alſo vnallowable in this caſe, both for that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle wils vs, that <hi>Seruitus nostra ſit rationabilis,</hi> and likewiſe foraſmuch as Maiſter Arch-prieſts au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie was both obtained ſiniſterly <hi>ex parte</hi> of the Procurers, though not of his Holines graunt; and it as factiouſly adminiſtred euer ſince. The ground of which faction began ſince our good Cardinals death, firſt of all in <hi>Wisbicb,</hi> where the Ieſuits being taught <hi>vindicta diuina; Aemulari cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſmata meliora</hi> then iuriſdiction ouer the ſecular Clergie (they being religious, and ſo within the compaſſe of an expreſſe Canon to the contrarie of ſuch ſubordination) haue ſince procured this Arch-prieſtſhip by ſleight and ſurreption at his Holineſſe hands, and inueſted it in Maiſter <hi>Black-well</hi> to their vſe. This is that man, who to ſhewe himſelfe no leſſe gratefull to thoſe Fathers his Founders for ſuch his office, then hee hath ſhewn himſelfe moſt glad and greedie of the ſame, hath by auowing their wrongs againſt the Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants, notably preiudiced the Catholicke Church of late here amongſt vs, and like an vngentle birde berayed his owne neſt. Whereby both for the one and the other, he hath brought himſelfe to be alſo a triable partie together with them at the Apoſtolike barre; who elſe (had he been the man hee ought) might for all the blemiſh of his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſing, haue been admitted of both parties for competent Vmpier betwixt them of al aggriefes.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:178002:3"/> But ſee what a thing Ambition is, and how ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill are the obligations that it makes. Herehence is all the Catholicke Church on fire amongſt vs at this inſtant, whiles the Ieſuits hauing offred the wrong, maiſter Arch-prieſt in obſequious corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence to them for being ſuch their creature, maintaines that wrong againſt his own brothers; ſo much againſt all nature is his loue rather in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent then deſcending.</p>
            <p>Herehence haue proceeded his thundring ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſions, and preiudiciall decrees againſt them, to the intangling in a thouſand ſcruples the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of the ignorant, and leſſe learned ſort of Catholickes; herehence the bandiyng of lay and cleargie one againſt another throughout the Realme; herehence the vnchriſtian calumnies, and reproches, together with the withdrawing of wonted charitie on the Ieſuits partie, or rather their more &amp; more drawing to them by flat fraud and rapine, <hi>quae ſua ſint, non quae dei.</hi> Briefe; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hence is proceeded the lamentable domage to all our Church, both in her former and future fruits amongſt vs, for which all Proteſtants (being the <hi>Chorus</hi> hereunto) lowdlie laugh vs to ſcorne. Whiles (God he knowes) theſe good Fathers the Appealants in their wiſdomes and charitie can aduiſe no fitter meanes to right all theſe ſcandals together with their innocence, then their preſent appeale, being taught by former experience how that to compremize aggriefes amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues here at home, or to ſend priuatelie to <hi>Rome</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſame, is but to make the Ieſuits way to farther miſcarriages, and giue their inſolencies
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:178002:4"/> the more ground: whiles namelie father <hi>Cowbuck</hi> their brother ſerues them as goaler for our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plainants at <hi>Rome,</hi> and here in <hi>England</hi> M. Arch-Prieſt is no head ouer them to checke their exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitance, but at their curteſie (they hauing made him that head he is) but he rather a votary Fautor of all their miſdoings, whereby they reſt here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs the moſt lawles and incorrigible men in the world.</p>
            <p>But oh (ſay ſome of them) there is a General of our order, called <hi>Aqua-viua,</hi> who vpon complaint to him, is to order vs in any part of the world whereſoeuer, if we miſdoe. Forſooth, a goodlie reference: an Italian man liuing in <hi>Rome,</hi> to be complained vnto of wrongs done here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which were a matter both exceeding chargeable and hazardous, in regard of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance betweene, and likewiſe vnlikelie of due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe, he being no whit Engliſh, nor otherwiſe competent for the ſame. Beſides, that ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints to be carried to the Ieſuits General by our Prieſts, were to thrall the Eccleſiaſticall libertie to their iuriſdiction, in that it might ſeeme <hi>Agnitio Authoritatis</hi> to them (being religious) which were abſurde.</p>
            <p>Seeing then the Ieſuits here in <hi>England</hi> haue no other lawe nor awe in their carriages then their owne conſciences, it is no maruell if they haue giuen theſe ſcandals, eſpecially hauing two ſuch Patrons, the one heere, the other at <hi>Rome,</hi> as aforeſaid. Yet, who would euer haue thought that in a Religious ſocietie, ſo titularly profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Ieſus aboue all other Chriſtians, there could
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:178002:4"/> haue bin found ſo <hi>notabiles percuſſores Cleri?</hi> Was it fit (trow yee) for a Religious perſon, ſo vncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably, and ſo vnlearnedly, as hee hath done, to taxe by libell ſo many reuerend Prieſts as thirtie: I may ſay one hundred, ſo deepely in their repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, as by expreſſe tearmes of Schiſme, Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, &amp;c. to the Catholicke Church? And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; after a pacification of the ſaide ſcandall (whereunto the good men though much to their priuate preiudice, yet for the generall peace of the Church were willing) another of the ſame ſocietie with many other their fautors at their inſtigation to reuiue the ſame ſince to the paſſe it is now come? Or were the Prieſts ſo incorri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible men, as (were it true that they were Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matickes, Rebels, &amp;c.) there was no priuater meanes left to reclaime them, nor no charitie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then by libell? they offering to purge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of ſuch imputations by diſputation, which was denied them by maiſter Arch-prieſt, as a tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous requeſt. Againe, if they were ſuch, yet what had a Ieſuit to doe to cenſure them, being no head but a member, and that not of theirs, but of another bodie, and but onelie a borrower of their inſtitution and honours in comming thus to <hi>Englands</hi> vinyeard, their owne not being ſo worthie? Surely, the Ieſuit thought that <hi>Propter quod vnumquodque tale, &amp; illud magis tale;</hi> that Maiſter <hi>Blackwel</hi> hauing his authority from them, <hi>à fortiore</hi> hee might adminiſter the ſame. Be it ſo, yet was it not competentlie, nor condignely ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred in that manner, as by a libell ſo deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pightfull, and ſo vnlearned; as for the vnlearned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:178002:5"/> whereof, I can (ſure) make no other of it, then <hi>paenam peccati</hi> to the authour for the ſpite. Had he bin borne into the world with teeth &amp; nailes, his ſpirit could not haue beene more Satyricall, nor yet his tearmes through malice more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchollerlike. And for ſuch the learned vniuerſitie of <hi>Paris</hi> hath cenſured the tract both to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours and the Fautors diſgrace.</p>
            <p>Greatlie therefore was Maiſter Arch-prieſt to blame to giue it cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance at the firſt; but more, ſince the ſaid cenſure. Who but hee would haue ſhewed himſelfe ſo abiect minded for office, not procurable, but already procured, as to engage his exiſtimation in ſo foule a defence of but his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactors againſt his owne brothers, &amp; ſo famous an vniuerſitie? Call yee this either in the one or the other <hi>fraterna correctio?</hi> is this <hi>vna</hi> or <hi>altera admonitio?</hi> is this <hi>Dic eccleſiae?</hi> wherby ſo vertuous, ſo learned, and ſo manie Confeſſors of Chriſt to be at once denounced, as Ethnicks &amp; Publicans? Could the Fathers aduiſe vpon no worthier re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge againſt the Appealants for their concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with God almighties miracle againſt their ambition in <hi>Wiſsbich,</hi> wherein to make vſe of the Arch-prieſtſhip, then thus by Libell? Or could Maiſter Arch-prieſt alſo againſt the ſame parties, for their not acquainting him with their counſell concerning a ſubordination to be porcured from <hi>Rome</hi> (hee weening himſelfe worthie to haue bin not onelie a partie in that conſult, but the verie head and ſoule thereof, as ſhould ſeeme by his <hi>Concaleat ſtomacho</hi> vnto them ſince) be ſo groſſe in his reuenge, as to ſupport ſuch a libel? Ah poore
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:178002:5"/> aduiſe, or rather too prodigall ſpite. Ceaſe (Coſin) ceaſe henceforth thoſe your Fathers their equiuocation to the world, whereby vnder colour that the Arch-prieſt is a ſecular-Prieſt, they would haue his authoritie thought to ſhine but oblique toward their Societie, and too direct toward the Seminaries, in matters that may ariſe in difference betweene them; ſeeing both his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taindour to that dignitie was <hi>ex profeſſo</hi> procured by their meanes; and but interpretatiuely by the Prieſts (as their Agent himſelfe hath confeſt) as alſo his homely adminiſtration thereof in thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uowing their libell, and other his partiall carriage in their behalfes againſt them euer ſince aſſeuers the contrarie. But <hi>Iustus eſt dominus, &amp; iuſta iudicia eius;</hi> the Blacke-well or pit that they digged for others, themſelues are fallen into; being like to learne ere long what it is <hi>Mentiri in ſpiritum-ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum,</hi> as too flatly they haue done in abuſing the Apoſtolike Sea, by ſuch their interpretatiue col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loguing with it for the ſaid Authoritie toward the maintaining of libell and faction. Which neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe foraſmuch as it was well graunted by his Holineſſe, though ill obtained by them (he do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in opinion of their honeſt information whereof they failed) I liſt not here to diſpute it with you, but in reuerence to <hi>Rome</hi> admit it with all faults in full force and vertue, ſeeing the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealants themſelues (being the parties moſt wronged) haue ſo done, not doubting but his Holineſſe, (as hee is wholy Clement) will vpon due information aſwell touching the ſaid Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, as other their aggriefes therewith complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:178002:6"/> right both them in eſpeciall, and all our Church in generall againſt the Ieſuits, and Arch-prieſt, happily with the demolition of that Arch erected on ſo muddie a foundation. Suffice it, that in the meane time we hold ſuch an Authoritie fit enough for ſuch a manner of adeption, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration; and too preiudiciall both to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate of our Church, and the future of our Countrey: and as for his auowrie of the libel, the ſame to be both vnclerkly, and vnnaturall; yea and ſchiſmaticall in him, ſubiect to farre more ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions as well to all our Church, as to the Complainants, then he and his twelue Aſſiſtants are euer able to make. Such a douſen to ſuch a thirteenth was neuer ſeene in the Church of God to this day, either for Eccleſiaſticall or ciuill facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but what ſhall I ſay? <hi>Imparum infida amicitia,</hi> and therefore like head, like hornes. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in may we comfort vs, but to thinke that (in his Holineſſe prouidence) ſuch a head of faction will not long holde. It is but our patiences of the Laytie in the meane time, by the example of our Ghoſtly Fathers the Appealants, and our zealous vnion with them againſt ſo foule a ſcandall. The firſt, though the Ieſuits and Arch-prieſt deride as a vertue perforce (they for their parts not broo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to be forced to any vertue) yet the latter hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they may rue. As for Patience, it is certaine that Father <hi>Cowbuck</hi> asking the two meſſengers at <hi>Rome</hi> his Priſoners vpon what hope of friends, or countenance they came thither about ſuch a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines; and they anſwering their Innocence onely and the goodneſſe of their cauſe, he laught both
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:178002:6"/> them and ſuch their anſwere to ſcorne. Euen ſo likewiſe Maiſter Arch-prieſt here at home. Oh, (ſaith he by his Agents) cannot Seminary Prieſts profeſſing ſo paſſiue a ſpirit of perſecution and Martyrdome for Chriſts cauſe (as they doe in their very inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) put vp ſome wrong for Ieſus ſake. Truely yes: were it not that in caſes of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall <hi>Beatius est non dare quàm accipere</hi> (howſoeuer the Ieſuits in money matters holde it other) and alſo, ſo long as the perſecution proceeds not from a ſocietie of Ieſus, and in Ieſus name; a name which hath alwaies throwne out diuels, neuer brought in any. It is no waies fit that ſo glorious a name ſhould be thus abuſed, as to be made vſe of <hi>ex parte dati ſcandali:</hi> and more tolerable were euen murder at an enemies hands then at a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, moſt of all at a Fathers, ſuch as all Ieſuits (though but ſcore-yearlings) call themſelues.</p>
            <p>Haue the Seminaries bred vp Maiſter <hi>Blackwell</hi> and his douſen Aydants, thus in ſteede of being themſelues Martyrs to martyr others? And what others? Their own Brothers: and how? In Ieſus name. Good Cardinall <hi>Allan</hi> neuer founded the Seminaries for ſuch impietie, nor yet endowed he them by his Preſidence with ſuch a ſpirit; who (doubtleſſe) were he now aliue and ſawe this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figure in his broode from his inſtitution ſo all of loue, ſo all of charitie, would ſcarſe know it to be his, or knowing it would weepe ſalte teares, and repent him at the heart that euer he coupled Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its therewith, who euen in his life time began to diſtaſte their factious faſhions, and namely nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly Father <hi>Cowbuck.</hi> At a word (my good Coſin)
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:178002:7"/> little reaſon haue the Seminaries to ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſo mute and neutrall toward their Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant-Brothers in this buſineſſe, as moſt of them haue done till now of late, ſeeing that euen as ſuch, the Libeller (if they marke it) aſſeuers them to be no leſſe then Rebels too; much leſſe ſo very oppoſite as many of them are, and notably the twelue Aſſiſtants, of whom not one (that I heare) is a partie for them: little reaſon (I ſay) haue they or theſe to be ſuch, conſidering that therein they betray their owne and the Seminaries honours wholy to the honouring of the Ieſuits, and forget that <hi>implicitè</hi> euery one of themſelues in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar is inuolued in the ſame diſgrace. For, to haue it ſpread throughout all the Chriſtian world, that thirty Engliſh Seminaries are at one clap become Schiſmaticks, Rebels, &amp;c. to the Catholicke Church, what a blot will it be aſwell to all that are of the nurſerie, as of the number? and in eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, how much may it contriſt the holy Ghoſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Seminaries, and alſo iuſtly alien from them their benefactors were ſuch a ſcandall true? Namely, the Popes Holineſſe how deepely may he feele it in his Apoſtolike and paternall ſpirite. Whereas on the other ſide it not being true, that ſo many, yea or any of the Libellés are ſuch Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matickes, Rebels, &amp;c. to our holy mother as the libeller doteth, how heartily ought the whole bodie, and all the members of the Seminaries ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaude the ſame, and vnanimouſly concurre to propulſe the reproch. But (alas) too many of them (we ſee) are bought and ſolde to the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its thus from their brothers, and their owne ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:178002:7"/> they hauing the Eccleſiaſticall purſe of our Countrey wholy in their pocket, like the Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in Scripture, who betrayed his and our good Lord and Maſter, and theſe others ſo deiect, nay abiect mindes. For, were they truly zealous, it were poſſible enough for them to hold out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the double perſecution (to wit) both that of the Proteſtant, and this of the Ieſuits and Arch-prieſt, with and for their brethren, eſpecially ſuch brethren as (without offence be it ſpoken) are the very creame of our Clergie. Not that I thinke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them ſo vnlearned, no not of the Aſſiſtants, (who it ſeemes were moſt called to the place for their inſufficiencies, though in faith ſufficient e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for ſuch employment) as to iudge the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealants Schiſmaticks, &amp;c. by the booke, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to be parties againſt them, or neuters; but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of meere puſillanimitie. This <hi>Mammon</hi> is ſuch a Monarke, that it bribes and bridles all but Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puchines, tainting their humours and honours both; eſpecially where Authoritie concurres, as in this wrong of the Ieſuits Maiſter <hi>Blackwels</hi> (ſuch as it is) doth; who whom their largeſſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lures, or parfimonie not, his Authoritie makes good in each. For, as for his late anſwere to the Appealants booke, that importeth no ſuch rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or ſatisfaction why they ſhould thinke his proceedings, and conſequently their partie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto any waies iuſt againſt their brethren; it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing onely a meere oſtentation of his Arch-prieſtſhip, and a bare <hi>Ipſe dixit,</hi> and nothing elſe; fo full is euery line beſides of abſurdities and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions as touching the matter; onely the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:178002:8"/> of the Doctors hee hath therein not vſed, whereby nor abuſed, which is a maruell.</p>
            <p>Great pittie therefore it is, and a ſcandall; our Cleargie (which for being a perſecuted Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie ſhould be the more vnite as <hi>per antiperiſteſin</hi>) to be found guiltie in this caſe ſo much concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their honours, of that vice which the Scot noteth nationall and naturall to our people (that is) like dogges all to take part with the iniuring dogge againſt the iniured; or rather not like hogs (which quoth he the Welchmen are) to ayde the fugitiue and weaker hogge againſt the ſtronger. Great pitie likewiſe and a ſhame it is vnto our Seminaries, who being <hi>Luminare maius</hi> in our Fermament then the Ieſuits, they notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to eclipſe and obnubulate them therein, by diſſeuering them, as thus by libell they haue done. Briefe, that Ieſuits who in their inſtitution are but Confeſſors <hi>(vz.)</hi> but Graduates, <hi>Beſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>os</hi> and Proficients towarde perfection, ſhoulde dare ſo baſely to blemiſh the Seminaries, whoſe inſtitution is far more hautie <hi>(vz.) Paſcere gregem</hi> and <hi>ponere animas ſuas pro ouibus ſuis,</hi> which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies perfection alreadie acquired; as, then which, <hi>maiorem charitatem nemo habet:</hi> they (I ſay) to ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh them ſo libelliouſly as is ſaid, not onely by ſeuering them thereby one from another, but (which worſe is) by ſetting them one againſt another.</p>
            <p>Is Chriſts ſupreme Vicar in earth a ſecular Clearke, yea, ſo farre forth ſecular, as being once choſen out of a Monaſticke-order to that Sea (for a Ieſuit Pope neuer yet had yee any)
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:178002:8"/> ſtraight his Monaſticke-nature dies. And alſo are all Biſhops vnder him in the Vniuerſall Church ſuch, whereby they haue authoritie (as ſuch) to viſit and correct the religious perſon, and not the religious them; that thus the religious ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult ouer our Seminaries (being likewiſe ſuch) and that without encounter, nay with their own aſſents? I ſpeake it boldlie, and I hope, <hi>abeſt inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia verbo;</hi> not ſo glorious by ods is the Ieſuits ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie as the Seminaries, either for inſtitution, or practiſe (eſpeciallie practiſe here in our countrie) whatſoeuer it be elſewhere. For the inſtitution, as afore is touched; for practiſe, as for example. Shew yee mee from Father <hi>Ignatius</hi> time their founder to this day (which is now well nigh a hundred yeeres ſince) halfe ſo many Martyrs tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughout the whole world in all that time of the Societie, as haue beene of our Seminaries within theſe thirtie yeeres here in our countrie: omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that euen to this day, there is not ſo much as one Canonized Saint of the order, Confeſſor, or Martyr; no not their founder himſelfe: whom neuertheleſſe with a great manie moe of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie, I reuerentlie thinke to be ſuch, and as ſuch, doe verie humbly commend me to their praiers. Which defect of honour to their Order (which all other religious Orders haue) they would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe by ſaying (as ſome of them haue done) that the Canonizing of Saints is but a ſuperfluous pompe in the Church, which may verie well be ſpared. Wherein (ſurelie coſin) beſides that it founds hereticallie and againſt Catholicke reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, they haue little reaſon euen in moralitie,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:178002:9"/> ſeeing that euery gallant Champion is well wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of his Bay. And therefore as little reaſon haue they to beare themſelues ſo ſuperlatiuely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all other holy Orders, were it but for the Puneiſme of the ſocietie, which blemiſh to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teruaile together with all other blemiſhes in it, they haue giuen it the name which is aboue all names, and holy aboue all holies, the name Ieſus. In which name well I graunt them they may iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and victoriouſly goe againſt all Gods enemies, but not againſt his friends; eſpecially bearing no more croſſes along with them whereſoeuer they goe, then we ſee they doe: <hi>quaerentes</hi> in moſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>quae ſua ſunt,</hi> rather then <hi>quae Dei,</hi> both wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and wealth. Whereby they haue purchaſt them a hard opinion of all religious Orders, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo farre forth as to be written againſt by ſome of them in moſt parts of Chriſtendome <hi>ex pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſo,</hi> and in particular are baniſht for ſuch out of all the moſt Chriſtian Kingdome of <hi>France,</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for their Spaniſh faction there; where for all their great meanes, and flattering Ballades of late made and exhibited to the King, they are not like to get in againe this yeare, nor yet the next, hee hearing of their turbulent carriage here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Onely they holde in here and there with the good Capuchines (being at oddes with all other orders, and oftentimes among themſelues) which is their greateſt credit, and which they may eaſily doe, for that (as one of thoſe good Friers on a time confeſt) they couet to haue all, and theſe nothing. Vpon this grounde likewiſe it was that the excellent good Biſhop of <hi>Bamberge</hi> in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:178002:9"/> being laboured vnto ſome fewe yeares agoe, by the importunat commendations of the houſe of Auſtrich, and other Catholicke-ſtates of the Empire, for their admittance into his moſt refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med dioceſſe, he anſwered; no, I brooke no ſuch Quiddits.</p>
            <p>To conclude then with that I began to ſay; ſeeing the Ieſuits are a ſocietie ſo inferiour to all other religious Orders, and yet ambitioning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue them all in the bare name of Ieſus, ſcorning (belike) in their ſingularitie to bee called after their founder, hee being as yet no canonized Saint (as aforeſaid) and namely an Order farre inferiour to the Seminaries both for inſtitution and merit to our Church and Countrey (as alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die is partly proued) though not in priuiledges from the Sea Apoſtolicke (wherein howſoeuer otherwiſe they come ſhort in merits to other or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, it will be ſure to be neuer a whit behinde to any) it is (I ſay) great puſillanimitie in the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the ſame, <hi>cedere ſuo iuri</hi> ſo much, as to giue them the preheminence in our Countrey for ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall rule, either in their owne name, or to their vſe, as Maiſter <hi>Blackwels</hi> is; much more to ſuffer themſelues to be ſo infamed by them as by flat libell, and which worſe is, by their owne par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking therewith. Is it not enough that the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its diſgrace and ſupplant them with their zizani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aes in their owne Colledges, liuing vnder their Ferrule; that they expell them thence at their pleaſures; that they beate them almoſt to death; but alſo in their Countrey they will aſſay the like? and euen not there manumize them from their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:178002:10"/> wrongs; <hi>Pharao</hi> himſelfe being no longer cruell to the Iſraelites, then whileſt they liued in his land, ſaue once, when in reuenge thereof the red Sea miraculouſly deuoured him, and all his hoſt. Is it not enough that for euery one Martyr of thoſe Fathers, there haue been twentie at leaſt of theſe Brothers to our Church, and yet they to vſurpe the honour of all, like the Spaniſh-Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in the Lowe-countries, who hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies the leaſt part in his Lieges ſeruice there, and yet the moſt in the praiſe? Is not all this (I ſay) and a great deale more of the Ieſuits vnkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and vndeſeruings both of our Seminaries, our Church and Countrey, enough; but needes to al this they muſt adde libelling vpon them too, forgetting that <hi>Qui dixerit fratri ſuo Racha</hi> is <hi>reus gehennae ignis?</hi> I could wiſh, and I verily hope they will valew themſelues aboue the Iaponian, and other Indian Clergie, who know no other Pope then the Ieſuits, and take their bare words for Canons. At leaſt I could wiſh that in this caſe of ſo reall reproch to their whole bodie, and preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to their Apoſtolike-harueſt in our vineyard here, they would (as I hope in God they will, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuring <hi>Mammon,</hi> and all other ſiniſter allure, and adiure of both Ieſuit, and Ieſuited Arch-prieſt) ioyne with their wronged brethren in a confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and vnanimous defence, and not ſuffer their honours which is alſo their owne, ſo baſely to be bandied out of our Church and Countrey; namely, by an intruding ſocietie, were it but in honour of their excellent Founder, our late Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall, a man no whit inferiour to their Father
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:178002:10"/> 
               <hi>Ignatius,</hi> but rather afore him in all manner of rare deſert to the Sea-Apoſtolicke, for which hee was worthie to die a Peere of the ſame: <hi>à fortiore</hi> then, they being the naturall broode of our Engliſh Church <hi>ex traduce</hi> from Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> and <hi>Mellitus,</hi> continued rather then founded by the ſaid good Cardinall to our Countrey in all this age of perſecution. Surely (Coſin) rather then this ſhall come to paſſe through the indiſcreete o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, or rather puſillanimitie of the Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries themſelues toward the Ieſuits; there will not want amongſt the Catholicke-laitie ſpirites to vndertake the defence, in honour both of our Church and Countrey, and namely of the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealants our ſo reuerend Patriots, and ghoſtly Fathers: who, though they for their parts haue all this while been content in their exceeding charitie, but to holde the buckler to their eares againſt the Societies blowes; yet theſe haply will not ſticke to returne them in their behalfes a ſound venny at leaſt. Yea, ſeeing thoſe Fathers haue thus preſumptuouſly broken quarter with ours, and that in our owne Countrey (they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing meere Spaniſh) let them either yet make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends (if at leaſt it be not too late) or elſe be ſure that they ſit faſt; for that (<hi>ſaluo</hi> the Appeale) they are like to carrie as good as they bring, for all our good Cardinall be dead and gone; ſuch being <hi>Lex talionis; dens pro dente, oculus pro oculo:</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine a meere morall iuſtice, that <hi>Quiſquis quae non licet loquitur, quae non lubet audiat.</hi> We Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes ſtanding as yet on the one ſide of the Riuer (the Appeale depending) and the Ieſuits on the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:178002:11"/> other, I doe not doubt but God will giue vs the day when once we come to cloſing; or if not, at leaſt God ſhall loſe no honour by our foyle, ſo humbly will we all with our Appealant-Fathers yeeld vs obedient to the diſgrace, and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicke Sea; which ſpirite (I pray God) they beare. The Societie hath giuen ſcandals enough, and daily doth throughout all the parts of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, which if they were but halfe made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a noſegay, would (I doubt not) yeeld ſo vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorie ſent vnto Engliſh noſes, that we ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme ſuch flowers not worth the ſetting in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> garden. But this debt they may yet foreſtall if they will, and all harder meaſure that may therewith befall them, by licking out their <hi>Racha</hi> ſo irreligiouſly written, and more impudently maintained againſt our Fathers, and withall ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue themſelues in ſo doing, from their <hi>reatus ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hennae ignis.</hi> Well, <hi>ipſi viderint.</hi> They know very well that <hi>Non dimittitur peccatum niſi restituatur ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latum,</hi> and that confeſſion of a fault is the leaſt part of Pennance, ſaue letting the wrong fall; which (we ſee) they would now gladly doe, if that would ſerue the turne, but it will not; for that as the French man ſaith: <hi>Desbender l'arque ne guerit pas le play:</hi> To vnbend the bowe, heales not the wound. More charitie were it in them by a penitent confeſſion, though with the leſſe ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction (which once our Fathers for peace-ſake would haue accepted) they to ſhame the Diuell rather then themſelues ſtill by the contrarie: for to ſtand vpon Puntoes in ſinne, eſpecially ſuch a ſinne as brings Schiſme with it, what a ſhame is it
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:178002:11"/> for a religious perſon in a perſecuted church; who though it were no wrong at all, but right that he hath written, yet had he Saint <hi>Paules</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, who wiſhed <hi>Anathema eſſe pro fratribus ſuis;</hi> he would not ſticke to confeſſe it a fault (though none) and alſo ſatisfie for it as ſuch: much more Maiſter Arch-prieſt (the matter being bad) had he the ſpirit of that good Pope, who of an Arrian-Prelate (as he was) being by the ſtrong hand of the Empreſſe <hi>Eudoxia</hi> (as I remember) exalted to the Sea Apoſtolicke, was no ſooner inueſted therin, but did ſtraight renounce his Arrianiſme, and decree the Catholicke faith againſt it; had he (I ſay) but halfe his ſpirit, he would now in his authenticke authoritie doe both himſelfe and his brethren right in this matter againſt the Ieſuits his makers, howſoeuer afore time he ſtoode for them in the wrong. But he is all for <hi>Gloria patri,</hi> and as for <hi>Filio</hi> hee ſeemes the flat Arriane, for which great pittie it is, that <hi>Fratrum quoque gratia rara est.</hi> Nay, hee that can penne expreſſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and vtter them openly in blemiſh of the partie preſent (being a Gentlewoman of Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in this land) which (as ſhe her ſelfe hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted) was the onely cauſe of her turning Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant: he alſo that can by his letter expreſſely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge one of his Aſſiſtants (as he did) to calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niate and defame a certaine reuerend Prieſt by name (whom I know) he (I ſay) that can thus do, no maruell if ſuch a Iudge be of counſell to a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell, and a countenance thereunto. No maruell alſo if he be an vnfortunate Father to his ghoſtly children, as to one he was to my knowledge, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:178002:12"/> that I rue; who after a long and worſhipfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Catholicke faith in the Towre of <hi>London</hi> and other priſons, in the end fell vnder his hand. Laſtly, no maruell if ſuch a one for want of good neighbours be faine to praiſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as lately hee hath done, and that in the firſt place too, afore his founder Father <hi>Parſons,</hi> in a certaine tract intituled <hi>Pius griefe,</hi> which by the confuſed huddle of the Doctors ſayings therein, and the ſtile, is held to be his.</p>
            <p>But to the Ieſuits againe. <hi>Dico meam culpam</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their owne leſſon, and ſo boyiſh a pennance, as they vſe it, me thinkes they ſhould not ſhame to ſay it when it comes to their turnes, as now through their miſdoing it doth; much leſſe ſhuld they perſiſt ſo ſtiffe-necked in <hi>defenſione peccati,</hi> it being a ſinne in the higheſt degree againſt the holy Ghoſt. But ſeeing they doe ſo, as chuſing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſhame themſelues then the Diuell (ſuch is their charitie) truly (Coſin) I doe not ſee, but ſome lay-cauterie as well as the religious Appeale depending, is requiſite to be applied to them (as aforeſaid) though better a great deale, and more meritorious were voluntarie pennance from the heart, then that which ſo perforce they may haue cauſe to take to the heart. Some ſhew of grace they haue alreadie made in proffering a parley of peace to the Appealants; but it is indeede but grace in ſhew, nor <hi>gratia gratis data;</hi> but a meere ſeruile grace, extorted out of the iuſt feare they haue of the Appeale (which by Braues nor by their great friendes they ſee they cannot ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe) and alſo for the high iniurie they haue
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:178002:12"/> done to Saint <hi>Peters</hi> chayre touching the ſame; for which they are like to bee put to ſuch a pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance vpon the iſſue thereof (I feare me) as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides to ſee the Appealants faculties and honours reſtored vnto their innocence by the Apoſtolike Paſtor (which they haue taken away) theirs, and the Arch-prieſts <hi>vice verſa,</hi> to bee ſuſpended and attainted as Schiſmaticall, &amp;c. In which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicament I am perſwaded they haue been <hi>ipſo facto</hi> from the firſt: for which cauſe (for my own part, I aſſure yee Coſin) I make it a ſcruple in my conſcience to communicate with any of them in Sacraments till they be humbled, eſpecially the Ieſuits, holding it (as they do) lawfull <hi>vti ſcientia in confeſsione,</hi> as much to ſay as to make vſe of mens Confeſſions.</p>
            <p>As for Maiſter <hi>Blackwell</hi> himſelfe (ſetting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the libell which in the libeller was Schiſme <hi>primariò</hi> and <hi>principaliter,</hi> and alſo in his brother Father <hi>Cowbuck,</hi> for procuring himſelfe to be gao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler at <hi>Rome,</hi> to the precurſor-meſſengers thither touching Eccleſiaſticall libertie, together with his diſmiſſing them in the end from thence vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, diſgraced, yea, and with expreſſe prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to returne to their countrey, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exhibition to liue elſe where) ſetting this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide which was expreſſe Schiſme in them <hi>prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riò,</hi> was it not (I pray) if not Schiſme in Maiſter <hi>Blackwell</hi> (for that he is ſince a receiued ſuperiour, as may be obiected) at leaſt ſchiſmaticall in him <hi>ſecundariò,</hi> and as in vſe to Schiſmatickes, ſo farre forth in countenance of that libell, to diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance an Appeale made to his Holineſſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:178002:13"/> the ſame (all Appeale being <hi>intrinſecè, Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitio authoritatis</hi> in the higheſt degree to the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealé, and the greateſt Plea of Iuſtice both ciuill and eccleſiaſticall, that is, to diſcountenance it (I ſay) by ſuſpenſion of the Appealants faculties ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, and alſo their temporall reliefe from their friends for the ſame; to interdict ſo honourable a cenſure as that of the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Paris</hi> was toward the forwarding of the ſame Appeale; to diſwarne the Appealants booke, being dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his Holineſſe owne eye in the reall nature of an Appeale, to be read of the Catholickes of our countrey as ſchiſmaticall, nay hereticall; to ſlaunder the ſacred Sea with a flat lye, affirming that hee had receiued a reſolution from the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-Citie, againſt the ſaid cenſure of <hi>Paris</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the backewarding of the ſaid Appeale? Briefe, to approue the tract of Schiſme, whether true or falſe againſt his Brothers, it being to the ſo great and generall diſorder of our church both in the Cleargie and in the laytie, eſpeciallie the libelés, beſeeching him to call in the ſaid treaty ſo diſparageable to their reputation, and all the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries, together with their ſhewing themſelues corrigible by their offer of diſputation, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were ſchiſme or not, and his refuſall of each as aforeſaid? Was not all this (I ſay) with a great deale more, <hi>à primo ad vltimum</hi> ſchiſmaticall in him, as being to the diſunio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of an vnited bodie; at leaſt Excommunication to him as in preiudice of eccleſiaſticall libertie (in which nature al Appeale is) and (ſure) flat ſchiſme in them, <hi>viz.</hi> the Ieſuits, both for that cauſe, and alſo for that by their ſaid
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:178002:13"/> libell they on their parts principally procured the ſaid diſunio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Gods church here amongſt vs, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding the members therof one againſt another? Was not al this ſchiſme, &amp; ſchiſmaticall in him, or them, or both, whether the Appealants be Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks or no? Which (verily) they are not if theſe be, becauſe the queſtion is not <hi>ad diuerſa,</hi> but <hi>ad contraria in eodem ſubiecto, (vz.)</hi> whether in the caſe whereof they are both agreed, the Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants be Schiſmaticks or none. Nor ſerues the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon afore parentheſed of the Arch-prieſts now authentike headſhip for his excuſe from ſchiſme; for, though it may be graunted, that in ſuch caſes whereto his authoritie is of force (as it is but <hi>ad officia certa &amp; determinata</hi>) members to concurre with his miſguidance in thoſe caſes be no ſchiſme in him; but rather thoſe members ſchiſmaticall, that goe againſt the ſame (though iuſtly) the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in that caſe ſeeming to ſtand on his ſide in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his authoritie eſpeciall (as a head) to thoſe caſes, which vnitie they deuide by their oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: yet in a caſe which is meerely out of his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie (as a head) ſuch as this of the Appealants is <hi>in fundamento;</hi> to wit, he being therein a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall partie, and ſo not iuſt he to be his own Iudge, <hi>(vz.)</hi> as a head, Maiſter Arch-prieſt both may be, and (vnder correction) I take it, is a ſchiſmaticke (carrying himſelfe as he hath done) and all they that take with him though the greater number; for that herein he is to be taken not as a head (the matter not being in his iuriſdiction as ſuch) but as an equall member, and that triable like the reſt: ſo as his deuiding his fellowe-members in ſuch a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:178002:14"/> caſe not as a head (though a head) but as a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber himſelfe, from being an vnited body as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time; I doe not ſee why it ſhould not be ſchiſme in him; much more foraſmuch as this ſeparation both of himſelfe, and others from the vnited bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die by his partaking, and procuring part to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with the libell, was at the firſt when hee was indeede but a member, and no compleate head in <hi>eſſe,</hi> but only in <hi>potentia,</hi> and that in <hi>voto proprio</hi> more then any others <hi>(vz.)</hi> in the <hi>interim</hi> of the Cardinals conſtitutiue-letter, and his Holineſſe Briefe; ſo as it is not his being ſince an autenticke head can ſalue the Schiſme which he then incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as a member, eſpecially he perſiſting therein by expreſſe cenſures againſt the Appealants in the behalfe of the libell: but rather more and more the ſame is heauie vpon his now headſhip, by how much, <hi>Omne animi vitium tanto conſpectius in ſe Crimen habet, quanto maior qui peccat habetur.</hi> Nor euer was it holden in the Lawe, a good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittance of a widdowes debt; much leſſe a iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of her breaking (for example) her neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours wiues head in the time of her widdow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood <hi>(vz.)</hi> in the <hi>interim</hi> of her two Husbands, to ſay ſhe is now a remarried Wife: but ſo as her ſecond Husband is liable thereunto (as her head, and in her right) and he anſwerable for all the ſame. The like or very little different is this caſe of Maiſter <hi>Blackwels,</hi> whereby (I doe not ſee) but if he were a ſchiſmaticke in the <hi>interim</hi> aforeſaid as a member of the Seminaries, and (as ſuch) ſo notable an inſtrument of the Ieſuits who were ſchiſmatickes, and ſo hee a ſchiſmaticke in their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:178002:14"/> right though not his owne: <hi>à fortiore</hi> now (as a head) he is ſuch; he continuing the ſeparation (as ſuch) a great deale more: at leaſtwiſe take him as you will, head, or member, in the right or in the wrong; to impeach eccleſiaſticall libertie as he hath done in thwarting this Appeale, whether importing right or wrong in the Appealants (which the triall muſt ſhew) is Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to him, and all that take his part. And alſo whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a head neuer ſo autenticke, or his caſe neuer ſo good; he to ſuſpend an Appealant, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to cenſure him, yea, to decree againſt him <hi>lite pendente;</hi> was vniuſt dealing, and he ſubiect to Excommunication therefore <hi>ipſo facto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then againe for the Ieſuits, that they are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Schiſmatickes in this caſe; it is not their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clayming from being members of the bodie of the Seminaries, but of another bodie, <hi>vz.</hi> their owne ſocietie, that can excuſe them: for that, to be a ſchiſmaticall member to a bodie, it ſufficeth to be <hi>membrum genericum</hi> to that bodie, though not <hi>ſpecificum;</hi> and ſuch they are, being members of the Catholike Church with theſe; ſo that as ſuch they are Schiſmatickes in the caſe in the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they hauing made a ſeparation in the Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie-members, whereby the vnion of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die is in hazard to be diſſolued, and conſequently of our whole Church thoroughout <hi>England.</hi> To pleade that they are <hi>indiuidua vaga,</hi> and vndepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant of any bodie at all (as in truth they ſeeme to be here in <hi>England,</hi> ſo lawleſſe is all their carriage) would ſound much better for their not being Schiſmatikes, for ſo might they be held in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:178002:15"/> of Painters and Poets, of whom the verſe is: <hi>Pictoribus atque Poëtis Quodlibet audendi ſemper fuit aequa poteſtas.</hi> Or to ſtand vpon defence of the Tract, and ſo to thinke by maintaining it for good to cleere themſelues of Schiſme againſt the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Paris;</hi> that were moſt of all abſurd, neither ſhew they any ſuch want of wit &amp; grace, but rather labour all the wayes they can, and as farre as their Pride will giue them leaue, to hinder it from comming farther in queſtion; although their faction founded thereupon they no whit deſiſt, but rather augment it more and more for other their priuate intereſts. Or ſay, that they ſhould maintaine it good to the end, and to a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree at <hi>Rome</hi> on their behalfes; yet cannot that honour to them counteruaile one halfe of their miſchieuous carriages, &amp; the domages they haue done to our church in the meane time concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſame; ſo much may a good matter be marred in the ill handling; and ſo haue they done (were their caſe good) whileſt (for example) la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to proue there is a God, they raiſe vp the diuell: but their caſe is not ſo good, being ſimply bad; bad afore, and bad after.</p>
            <p>Briefe then, light the Schiſme where it will, on the Ieſuits, or Maiſter Arch-prieſt, or both; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it is that in the caſe of the Appeale, the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealants are none, both for the reaſons afore-al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged, and alſo foraſmuch as they doe Appeale. Moreouer if they were ſuch, what needed Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Arch-prieſt to ſuſpend them at all, they being ſuſpended <hi>ipſo facto</hi> for their Schiſme? Or what needed the Prouinciall of the Ieſuits, by his letter
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:178002:15"/> ſince crauing a reconciliation, acknowledge the Appealants <hi>zelatores gloriae Dei</hi> aſwell as himſelfe, or any of his; and as ſuch to recommend him (if I miſtake not) to their ſacrifices; ſeeing that all communication with Schiſmatikes, namely in deuotion (which is an act of Religion) is by an expreſſe Canon of the church inhibited to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes vpon paine of Excommunication, aſwell as all communion with heretikes in that kinde. Laſtly, if they were Schiſmatikes, what needed the Arch-prieſt and Ieſuits in their Implements, ſo lauiſhly to raile at the Appealants as Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants, and not as Schiſmatikes, as yet to this houre they doe; though with ſomewhat a lower and a hoarſe voyce, as almoſt out of breath. On the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſide, if it bee no Schiſme in them (as out of queſtion it is not) wherin then are the Appealants to blame to make their defence publike; the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence being publike (as is ſaid) both in ſubſtance, and in circumſtance to their publike reproch? Say, that the Libeller wrote it not in any ſuch ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit as of a libell, nor that he meant it ſhould euer become publike, being written but priuatly to his friend; yet it is not that can ſalue the blame, nor his, nor his Abbettors ſhames; ſeeing that howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, it becomming publike ſince, a publike ſtaine thereby inflicted vpon the parties by their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like defence thereof hitherto; and a publike pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident thereby giuen not only to detraction, but to all manner of vice beſides the Schiſme.</p>
            <p>Nor is the world ignorant of the Ieſuits querks in this kinde, they vſing to make ſhew of but done in priuat, and in ieſt, what they meane ſhould
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:178002:16"/> paſſe publike, and in earneſt, namely if the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be not iuſtifiable; as for example, Father <hi>Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bucks</hi> letter to Maiſter Doctor Biſhop at <hi>Paris,</hi> touching his excuſing the diſgraces done him at <hi>Rome</hi> as not proceeding from him (it being moſt falſe) did he not write his ſaid letter of vntrue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe vnto him, but firſt acquaint all <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> and a great part of <hi>England,</hi> with the contents thereof by copies, before euer the originall came to the Doctors hands; in ſo much as he knewe the ſubſtance thereof by ſundry both copies and reports of others, before he receiued the ſame? Alſo of later dayes, to colour their murderous batterie of Maiſter <hi>Lambart</hi> in <hi>Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manca,</hi> for not hindering certaine youthes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his prefecture there in the Colledge from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Benedictines (whom belike they had rather ſhould haue become Ieſuits being very towardly youthes) haue they not ſince his martyrdome herein <hi>England,</hi> falſified a letter of his by inſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thereinto certaine wordes, nay whole ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of their owne, in hyperbolicall and ſuper-exalted praiſe of their ſocietie, and ſo copied it abroad for his? True it is, and there is no queſtion but that the Saint forgaue them that outrage at his death, from the bottome of his heart; but how? Euen as Chriſt our Sauiour, and Saint <hi>Stephen</hi> by his example did their perſecutors, praying for them, and not as his ſo ſingular good friends and heauenly Patrons, as that forgerie would make him. Blame not then the Plaintifes for their publike defence by publiſht bookes; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is meete that publike wrong ſhould vſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:178002:16"/> publike meanes toward publike amends, and the rather, for that the Arch-prieſt ſince the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of thoſe bookes in his anſwere to them, boldly and brauely ſtickes not to ſay, that euen that booke to his Holineſſe was not like euer to haue come to his hands, but by his meanes; wherein hee moſt ſcandalouſlie derogates from the Popes honour, as to haue him thought his fellowe-Pupill to the Ieſuits.</p>
            <p>Now, whereas it is reproacht the Appealants, that in proceſſe of this their buſines of the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale, they pray (as it were) in ayde of my Lord of <hi>London,</hi> and other capitall Proteſtants in the Land, by vſing extraordinarie acceſſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce to and with them; it is true, that ſeeing the generaltie of Catholikes is ſo vnnaturally diſtaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of their innocence, it hath pleaſed God to raiſe them vp if not friends, at leaſt commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors <hi>ex lapidibus terrae;</hi> not that the parties ſo ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grieued, or any their friends, haue (I dare ſay) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued any domage thereby, but contrariwiſe ſome of them good turnes, and perhaps may in time more and more. Such is the ſpirit of theſe good men, <hi>vt retribuant bonum pro malo,</hi> and ſo good and great is God, and euer was toward di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed innocence, as to raiſe it vp friends <hi>citra ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectationem, in confractionem malignantium.</hi> So rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed he vp theſe latter yeeres <hi>England</hi> (the olde e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie of <hi>France</hi>) to ayde and eſtabliſh <hi>France</hi> her diſtreſſed King, againſt not ſo much a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious as a Spaniſh league, to the paſſe of peace he and it enioy now. And who knowes, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haply out of this ſo morall commiſeration
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:178002:17"/> of the Proteſtant, it may likewiſe pleaſe Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God by the miniſterie of theſe his innocents, to worke his extraordinarie and vnexpected glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in them, &amp; generallie to the Catholicke cauſe, <hi>qui potens eſt ex lapidibus istis ſuſcitare filios Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hae?</hi> As great, and as vnlikely matters as this hath the hand of God wrought, and namely in this kinde in Saint <hi>Euſtace,</hi> whom (as we reade in his Legend) God for his meere moralitie (being then a heathen man) called by famous miracle to his faith, and in the end crowned him a glorious Saint. And though the Ieſuits make vſe of this poynt in the Appealants reproch, inſinuating the conſequent Apoſtaſie of ſome of them euen at <hi>Paules</hi> Croſſe; and hereupon doe copiouſly diſcourſe to Catholickes in their vaine-glorie, how much more bleſſed a thing it is to be hated, rather then fauoured of heretickes, and the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, as they (for their parts they ſay) are, yet for all that, it is well knowne how much they labour the contrarie vnder hand at this inſtant, giuing out that what hope there is of a toleration to vs from the ſtate, is wholy by their meanes, and not by the Appealants; ſo cunning they are to make vſe of euery occurrent to their owne glorie, rather then their brothers, yea, or then Gods. It is very well knowne with what vaunt of their great friends and faculties both here at home and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, namely in the Popes, the Emperours, and other Chriſtian Princes Courts, they haue lately offered their ſeruice to the State, and that with what extreame extenuation of the Appealants their habilities, and friends to performe the like;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:178002:17"/> and withall it is well knowne what opinion the State hath of ſuch their offer; as alſo of their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Father <hi>Combuck</hi> his offering not many yeeres ſince by his letter and meſſenger (both which are yet extant) he to be her Maieſties true Intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer from <hi>Spaine.</hi> It were ſtrange if hee or they could ſo gull our State being ſo paſſing prudent; or that they could performe ſo notable contraries <hi>in eodem ſubiecto,</hi> as to deſerue well of <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>England</hi> both (being each others enemie) name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by malignant meanes to each vnder-hand, which as yet (we ſee) no indifferent and ſincere hand hath been able to doe. Notwithſtanding, admit that their Father-hoods, for all their hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to diſloyall and meere Spaniſh vndeſerts at out States hands, could thus worke themſelues in credit, and employment with, and by it; or that our State were driuen to ſo deſperate tearmes as to neede to vſe their ſeruices, hauing been and ſtill being ſuch manner of perſons; then were it (forſooth) no ſcandall at all, nor no degree from bliſſe to cooperate with heretikes; but contrarie wiſe they to be eſteemed for excellent men, men of high and deepe reach, of acute pollicie, of rare performance: briefe, the very angular-ſtone (which only Chriſt was) <hi>ex quo vtra<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fiant vnum.</hi> Whereas the Appealants to bee the men in that kinde, and ſo to Gods honour (as is expected at ſo good Prieſts, and Patriots hands) is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſed, and euen flat Reprobates.</p>
            <p>Be it ſaid then, vpon thus much feeling of the Ieſuits pulſe, that it is rather of enuie, then of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:178002:18"/> ſcorne; and leaſt of all of commiſeration or zeale, that they reproch the Appealants enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with Proteſtants; wherein (whether ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of the two it be, being vpon ſo vngodlie ground as their own meere glorie and intereſt, and not Gods) they ſhew their infinite vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; which (trulie) is no marueile. It is no marueile, if men ſo imprudent tranſgreſſors of the law of Charitie (as the Ieſuites haue hitherto appeared to be) and likewiſe of the law of Nature toward their Countrey (as now next ſhall be ſhowne) doe repine at morall vertue conſiſting of them both. No marueile, if they that haue croſſed In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence in S. <hi>Peters</hi> Court, doe depraue the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant-Compaſſioner thereof here in Chriſts Campe, though a great deale more iuſtifiable (yea nere awhit vnbeſeeming) are the Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants in the one, then they in the other; ſeeing that all aggrief, whether it be ſuſtained for right or wrong, deſerues pitie, and ſuch pitie is a vertue were it in the Diuell: whereas to barre a Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tife of acceſſe to the barre of Iuſtice, by impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him, and not ſuffering him to tell his tale (whether his caſe be good or bad, which cannot bee competently knowne except iuridically) was notable foule dealing in Father <hi>Cowbucke,</hi> and more then a Turke would haue offered. No marueile (I ſay) if thus debarring God (as it were) to do innocence right, they reproch moralitie in the Proteſtant, and the Innocent for making vſe thereof; ſo good Chriſtians they are both in the one and the other, and ſo oppoſite to Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:178002:18"/> Whereby I conclude, that that ſaying of S. <hi>Gregorie</hi> (I weene) <hi>Qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inima ſpernit, paulatim ruit in grauiora,</hi> doth no whit touch the Ieſuites in this caſe; ſeeing they, becauſe they will be ſure not <hi>ruere</hi> ſo, begin <hi>à grauioribus</hi> firſt <hi>(vz.)</hi> the breach of Charitie, and Iuſtice in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree (as is ſhowne) and ſo next proceede to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne moralitie, weening thereby (belike) and tis good policie too, with the greater blame to extinguiſh the leſſer, and to make it ſeeme but one.</p>
            <p>Beſides (which is another point of their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie) there hath not happened any perſecution, no nor the fall of any priuate Catholike through frailty in our church ſince this their Schiſme, but they impute it all to the Appealants, and to their entercourſe with Proteſtants; ſo viperous an ympe is Detraction, not ſo much in it ſelfe, as in theſe Fathers; who being the Detractors, ſeeme longe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> winded to hold out then Detraction it ſelfe. Neuer was an expreſſe vice ſo graced in the Clergie, nor ſo likely to be ſaincted as now; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning in a Ieſuite, and maintained by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike-Pregnatorie. What vice, nay what villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, deſerues ſo much as a ſcruple in the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the laytie, if this preſident hold good in the Religious? Or why ſhould Father <hi>Cowbucke,</hi> reading himſelfe taxt in the Appealants booke to the Popes Holines for a baſtard, and by intende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment à Parſons Sonne; for a binominous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; a perſon exploded, and expelled the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of Oxford with Bels for his turbulence;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:178002:19"/> and laſtly, a fugitiue perſon from the Armie of God here in our Countrie; all the ſame being moſt true, and thirtie perſons affirming it againſt his worſhip, being many againſt one, and they all Prieſts: ſeeing that one ſingle Ieſuite, and that a ſimple one too, hath dared to impeach euen thoſe thirtie, nay (God knowes) how many, of a farre fouler blemiſh then all thoſe put together, <hi>(vz)</hi> of Schiſme, Rebellion, &amp;c. to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church our holie Mother, and that moſt falſely and fooliſhly. And yet (forſooth) muſt his Libell paſſe <hi>Cum priuilegio Prothonotarij A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolici,</hi> in his ſlander ſo capitall and generall, as againſt ſo many worthie Prieſts; and alſo againſt the Cenſure of the famous Vniuerſitie of <hi>Paris</hi> to the contrarie: without that they may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their triall, or be fauoured in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence ſo much as of Proteſtants: and theſe others in their ſaid matter of truth, importing both a leſſer blame, and that not to a multitude, but to one ſole Ieſuite, it being readie to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerred face to face in the higheſt Court of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in the world <hi>(vz.)</hi> the Inquiſition; the ſame (I ſay) not only not to be beleeued, but alſo not allowed to be read amongſt Catholikes: ſo much the ſaid <hi>Parſon</hi> or Parſons-brat, and his Arch-prieſt for him, ſtand vpon the <hi>Puntillio</hi> of his Cardinalaticall hopes, againſt all faith and charitie.</p>
            <p>Oh God, how truly are the Ieſuites <hi>AEſops</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in this caſe to our good Fathers of the Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries, who bringing them home into this their
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:178002:19"/> houſe our Countrey, no ſooner felt they the warmth therof (that is) the fat of the ſoyle (which they ſeeme to reſpect more then the dew of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen) haue thus <hi>Inſidiati calcaneis eorum,</hi> and ſtung them for their loue. They like ſimple-ciuill Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh-men doing them at the beginning all the honour that might be, whereby to bring them (being ſtraungers) in acquaintance with our Countrey, as by the Appellatiue of Fathers (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) at euery word, and otherwiſe giuing them in all their meetings the preheminence and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hand (all but at Tyburne, which is a Poſt-paſt they are not greatly liquoriſh of (it ſeemes) nor worthie, as appeares by the few that haue ſuffered in all this time, and both by Father <hi>Haywood</hi> and <hi>Smith,</hi> their ſelfe-procured baniſhments from it, as ſitting downe (belike) in the eye of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their Nuptiall garment; and namely Father <hi>Cowbucke</hi> his puſhing the table from him, and flat running away, without ſo much as with a bare by your leaue, Sirs) haue wrought them ſuch an exiſtimation, as now (we ſee) cuts their throates, through their vngratefull making vſe of ſuch their curteſies againſt them. And ſo vaine a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are we, and euer were, to praiſe outlandiſh wares though leſſe good (nay bad) aboue our owne.</p>
            <p>But time and experience (I doubt not) will teach vs to be wiſer, kinder, and more religious; they being likely to ſhew vs ere long both in the preſent Appeale of our Prieſts, by that the Popes Holines haue iuſtly cut what they haue vniuſtly
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:178002:20"/> ſhufled and packt; and alſo by other our farther proofes (I feare me) with repentance if due pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention be not vſed, that the Ieſuits are a farre fitter Societie for <hi>India,</hi> then for <hi>England.</hi> And ſuch was our good Cardinals opinion of them, who much againſt his will (being then but Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Preſident) was ouer-ruled in conſorting them with the Seminaries for our Countrey; he for his owne part, holding it no fit tillage, <hi>Arare in bone &amp; aſino</hi> here in our Church, but all with Seminaries, conſidering that <hi>Pari iugo dulcis tractus.</hi> But in the meane time how little wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe, nay how great blemiſh this Schiſme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs is and will be to our Church (being vnder ſo ſharpe affliction) you partly ſee alreadie, and may imagine more, whether partie ſo euer preuaile. For what knowe we what vſe the State wil make therof, whether rather not to extinguiſh both by the meanes, then to tolerate any? All our comfort is, to thinke that the hand of God (whereunto no good thing is impoſſible) can and will in honour of the much blood of his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary-Saints that hath aſcended vp to him now theſe fortie yeeres out of our Church, ſtint ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames and turne all to the beſt; who perhaps permits the Societie and Arch-prieſt to be thus obdurate in their Schiſme, both to their finall ſhame, &amp; to the greater good of our Church and countrey, then yet we are worthy to apprehend. For (I aſſure yee Coſin) as touching the latter, <hi>latet anguis in herba,</hi> which but by this meanes could not well be deſcried. And though it ſeeme
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:178002:20"/> to vs but a matter vpon the By to the Appeale, yet (I doubt not) but it is a principall in the eye of God, and needing his eſpeciall interuention.</p>
            <p>It is (Coſin) at a word the whole ſtate of our Countrey, which the Ieſuits labour (whether in zeale to their Founder who was a Spaniard, or in gratitude to Spaines benefits, and generally of the houſe of Auſtrich to their ſocietie) to ſubiect to <hi>Spaine;</hi> and in ſuch faction, and in ſuch hope haue vnder pretence of Catholicke-Religion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie wonne vnto the Spaniard much ground in our Countrey; which (now that the plot is growne to a head in the Arch-prieſt) they ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie maintaine, and daily gaine more and more in the hearts of Engliſhmen. A ſhame that either Religion ſhould be ſo profaned, or Engliſh na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo ſtained: grace neuer vſing to preuaricate nature, but to accompliſh it.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore, as touching the Bull of <hi>Pius</hi> 5. and the ſame ſince confirmed by <hi>Gregorie</hi> the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth againſt her Maieſtie: as neither the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, nor any other forraine power is either by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, or implyed tearmes thereof incited to do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion ouer this land, as little are Engliſh hearts thereby diſallegeanced ſo from her Maieſtie, as to concur with any forraine Inuadour. For, though the ſaid Buls vpon her Maieſties Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therein promulged, doe <hi>de facto</hi> aſſoyle the ſubiects of this Realme from their homage vnto her; it therefore followes not that they muſt, and ought to be parties againſt her Maieſtie, and their Countrie to a forraine power, howſoeuer
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:178002:21"/> pretending euen Religion, or other ciuill good thereunto; for that were to conſter the Popes act ſo ouer-much in religion and grace, as to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of nature, which were againſt the Maxime aforeſaid. For, a man to goe againſt his owne Countrey, is and euer was holden in the ciuill part of the world an act <hi>Contra ius gentium:</hi> and alſo vnnaturall, yea and againſt all grace. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that Chriſt neuer did delegate any ſuch power to Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> as <hi>Tradere gentem in gentem,</hi> that being a meere temporall reuenge, and he but his Viccar ſpitituall. Yea, he expreſſely rebuked him for drawing his ſword, and cutting off <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas</hi> his eare. Chriſt ſaying vnto him, <hi>Tibi dabo claues regni caelorum:</hi> and <hi>Paſce agnos meos, paſce ones meas,</hi> ſounds cleane in another ſence. Moreouer, <hi>Mihi vindictam &amp; ego retribuam</hi> ſaith our Sauiour to all; <hi>à fortiore</hi> to the Cleargie: and by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet elſe where, <hi>Iustitia &amp; iudicium correctio ſedis eius; Ignis ante ipſum praecedet, &amp; inflammabit in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuitu inimicos eius, &amp;c.</hi> So as Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion againſt tranſgreſſing Kings and kingdomes, is no more then only to denounce by Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, and other the like Eccleſiaſticall cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, Gods diſpleaſure againſt them for their tranſgreſſion, and not to exerciſe the ſecular ſword at all: namely in ſuch a manner of reuenge as is ſaid, but leaue that to him who only hath power ouer Princes and Principalities, to conuert and ſubuert at his pleaſure. And euen the Sea A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolike it ſelfe hath been ſubiect to tranſmigra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſundry times vnder the hand of God, and as
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:178002:21"/> it hath ſeemed his angrie hand too, as well as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ſtates; the ſupreme Paſtors hauing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues been often forced to forſake <hi>Rome</hi> whileſt it was a ſacking, and euen at one clap were away at <hi>Auignion</hi> almoſt 80. yeares: which if tranſlation of States were ſo abſolutely in the Popes holines power, it is not likely he would (neither yet God) haue permitted his owne Sea to bee ſo diſpara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; ne would the demeſnes thereof be ſo ſmall as they are at this day.</p>
            <p>And whereas it may be obiected, that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Samuel</hi> elected, erected, and conſecrated <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> King of Iſrael in priuation of <hi>Saule</hi> for his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarication, <hi>ergo,</hi> the Popes holines may <hi>tradere gentem in gentem:</hi> that followes not, for that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this act of <hi>Samuel</hi> was ſuch a tradition (<hi>Dauid</hi> being a Patriot of Iſrael, and no forrainer) as alſo foraſmuch as <hi>Dauid</hi> did not execute that his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie in any ſuch manner as might argue blood and conqueſt, he hauing him ſundrie times in his power, &amp; might eaſilie haue ſlaine him if he had would; but as wee read expreſſelie in the ſtorie, did bemone, yea, and reuenge the death of <hi>Saul,</hi> and all becauſe he was Gods annointed; ſuch as her Maieſtie is ouer vs at this day, by the hand e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of a Catholicke Biſhop.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe the tranſlation of the Romaine Empire by <hi>Leo</hi> the fourth, to <hi>Charlemaine</hi> and his ſucceſſors, which was the greateſt tranſlation of temporall ſtate that euer was done by the Papall hand (for that of <hi>Constantines</hi> was of himſelfe in bountie to the Church) that (I ſay) of <hi>Leo,</hi> was
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:178002:22"/> no ſuch tradition as <hi>gentis in gentem,</hi> it being but titular onlie, and not in defeazance of the Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Empire, either in her Emperiall title, or demeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; the ſaid Empire continuing certaine hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeeres after in ech, till in the end <hi>vindicta di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uina</hi> diſſolued it, giuing it ouer for hereſie <hi>in verè alienam gentem</hi> both for rites and language <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Turke, who to this day is Lord of it all.</p>
            <p>I inforce not thus much vnto you (coſin) tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Popes holineſſe ciuill ſword, as to dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate any whit from it, or preſumptuouſlie to take vpon me to diſpute his Commiſſion otherwiſe then vnder correction, and in all ſubmiſſion to holie Church if I miſtake; but onlie in aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of S. <hi>Peters</hi> chaire and his keyes, vnto which I profeſſe a full and firme beleeuing ſoule, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence and reference whereunto, as alſo in loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all loue to my Prince and countrie, and zeale to the Seminaries fructification hitherto by the word, being likelie to performe it in time to a wiſhed end continuing as they haue begun, and with what els may happen Engliſhlie to the ſame end vpon the bie; I ſay againe I doe not ſee, how that that chaire &amp; thoſe keyes to be imbrude in blood, and to atchiue Conqueſts, eſpecially ſuch a tradition as of <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Spaine</hi> by the ſword, can any waies ſtand eyther with Chriſts, or his ſaid vicars honour.</p>
            <p>Againe, neither hath the practiſe of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Paſtours from S. <hi>Peter</hi> to this day beene ſuch that euer I reade: <hi>Ignem veni mittere in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, &amp; quid volo niſi vt ardeat,</hi> being a fire that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:178002:22"/> Chriſt neuer meant as out of two flints by reper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſion, or out of ſteele by hard-edge; but ſuch a fire as hee ſent downe in forme of diſparted tongues ouer his ſacred mother and the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like aſſemblie at Pentecoſt, and that which Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> our countries Apoſtle brought ouer to <hi>Eleutherius</hi> our king from Saint <hi>Peters</hi> ſea. Such is the fire that burnes in Ieſus name, and ſuch the fire that flames from forth the Seminaries a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs at this day. <hi>Volentes trahit</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi> of the holie ghoſt hauing his ſpirit) <hi>nolentes non cogit.</hi> The Ieſuits miſtake groſlie if they thinke that God is to come to his ſpouſe <hi>in turbine, &amp; tonitru,</hi> for ſuch ſhall be the comming of Antichriſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day, but in <hi>leui aura quaſi ſuſurrans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saxonie</hi> that was ſubdued to the Catholicke faith by armes how ſhort time continued it ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in? being the laſt of all the Germaine-Prouinces that receiued it, and the firſt that forſooke it. In like manner at this inſtant, hath not the <hi>Poland</hi> king receiued notable domage, and daylie doth, both in his owne and the Churches eſtate, at the hands of his natural ſubiects the <hi>Sweathlands,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the conduct of his vncle <hi>Fredericke</hi> whom they haue choſen their Protector (and as now the newes is their king) againſt him, comming at the Ieſuits inſtigation to conquer them to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike faith? Hath hee not loſt not onelie all that his naturall heritage (this of <hi>Poland</hi> being his kingdome but by election) from euer being by all likelihood Catholicke againe; it being now by meanes of ſuch his prouocation the rather roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:178002:23"/> in hereſie: but alſo part of <hi>Liefeland</hi> too which before was Catholicke, beſides his honour, and all his charges of warre? Such (forſooth) was the Ieſuits religion in this caſe, and ſo ſet they on the king to reuenge their wrongs rather then his, or Gods, and the irreuerence thoſe people did them (as they informd) comming to take place, and to preach amongſt them by vertue of the kings letters-patents.</p>
            <p>And thus if the Popes holineſſe had anie ſuch commiſſion (as is ſaid) the Ieſuits doe vſurpe it, they hauing (I am ſure) no <hi>Breue</hi> of his to ſhew, whereby thus to ſet kingdome againſt kingdome for religion, as <hi>Poland</hi> againſt <hi>Sweathland,</hi> and <hi>Spaine</hi> againſt vs. The knights of the Temple, &amp; of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> &amp; thoſe of <hi>Malta</hi> at this day (though they be the vowed ſouldiers of Chriſt &amp; his church) neuer bore ſo quarrellous and irreligious ſpirits: neither yet the Ieſuits founder though hee were ſometimes a ſouldiour, left them any ſuch rule. But leaſt of all is the Spaniard ſo peaceable a man amongſt his neighbours, as that hee neede to be nowd on to quarrels by the religious. Howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, that is not the way (coſin) the ſpirit of Chriſt being meeke and humble, and what manner of Ghoſpelling he propounded to his Apoſtles, and what armes (<hi>viz.</hi> a ſcrip and a ſtaffe) you may read in the Acts. Moreouer, if <hi>propter iniustitias, &amp;c.</hi> as in <hi>2. Reg.</hi> God to deliuer a nation ouer to the hands of another nation, be his curſe to that nation ſo giuen ouer, and not his bleſſing; is it meete that the Patriotts of the ſame ſhould exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:178002:23"/> themſelues inſtruments thereunto; all people being bound to complie with their countrie as with their mother in all Gods bleſſings, and not his maledictions?</p>
            <p>Now then, ſeeing it doth or may appeare vnto you, that the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> neither <hi>de facto</hi> hath, nor <hi>de iure</hi> can haue anie autenticke title, or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of title from the ſea-Apoſtolicke to the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Crowne of this land as for religion (which of all pretences is moſt forceable) much more eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and iuſtlie may you condemne the Ieſuits for perſwading amongſt vs a Spaniſh title thereunto in blood, which the Spaniard himſelfe neuer to this day yet pretended either in himſelfe or his predeceſſors: and laſtlie if ſuch their ſuppoſed title, together with the aforeſaid from the church faile, then (forſooth) the benefit of <hi>Spaines</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering vs, which of all other poſitions is moſt abſurde.</p>
            <p>Touching their title in blood then, were it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo new and ſo true, it is ſufficient anſwer ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto to ſay, that in reſpect they are meere ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and of another nation (I meane the king and his ſiſter both) ſuch their title is voide and of no effect, as well as for <hi>Fraunce</hi> to impleade their <hi>Sallicke</hi>-law in barre againſt <hi>Englands</hi> title vnto it. Againe, preſcription were alſo a compete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t eſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vnto them, they pretending from king <hi>Iohn,</hi> and <hi>Edward</hi> the third, and yet neither their ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors nor they themſelues hauing layed in their claime to this day, which during the deuiſion of the houſes of <hi>Lancaster</hi> and <hi>Yorke,</hi> at what time (it
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:178002:24"/> continuing long, and the whole land likewiſe therevpon deuided in ciuil warres) it was a fit ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for the Spaniard to haue done, &amp; ſet in foote, conſidering that <hi>vis diuiſa debilis,</hi> and alſo being then neerer the ſtemme of this pretended title, which would haue made the better ſhow. Briefe, if titles ſo farre fetcht might take place for a Crowne, I wiſſe there are in this land a manie poore perſons at this houre that might be ſerud before <hi>Spaine.</hi> And as for king <hi>Iohn,</hi> though hee were not the beſt Prince either to the Church or our Countrie, but vnfortunate to ech, and to him ſelfe moſt, yet will we not hold him ſo vnbleſt of God, and vnhappie, as that from his loyne ſhould be intituled a forraine-pretender to this realme: ne euer built hee London bridge for a Spaniſh Conqueror to trample on, as I haue often heard that nation boſt of ſuch a day. Much leſſe king <hi>Edward</hi> that our victorious king may his ghoſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide to ſee <hi>England</hi> vnder a forraine rule, who ſubdued forraine powers and Crownes to it. Be this enough ſaid and more then needs touching <hi>Spaines</hi> title in blood to <hi>England,</hi> ſeeing that euen a meere Engliſh pretendant to deduce a title ſo farre off, and after ſo manie changes amongſt vs, without making claime any time betweene were abſurd: much more ſo meere ſtrangers, &amp; preſent enimies as both they are to our ſtate: for which, as little reaſon wee haue as for their religious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence aforeſaid, to be any way parties to their raignes ouer vs.</p>
            <p>Touching their conqueſt then, and the vtilitie
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:178002:24"/> therof to our countrie (which is the laſt point the Ieſuits perſwade, the other two fayling) they doe well (verilie) to ſuggeſt it vtill at leaſt (if ſo) ſeeing that <hi>vulgus amicitias vtilitate probat,</hi> rather then honeſt and honourable which at all it would not be, but contrariwiſe a meere wrong in them to attempt, and ſlauerie in vs to endure. So noble an Iland as this, which (to vſe the Spaniſh Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphers owne words) was one of the 3. prime plumes in the helme of the Romaine Empire at her greateſt, the other two (quoth he) being <hi>Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Fraunce:</hi> an Iland which before anie of them was able to free it ſelfe from that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, hauing euer ſince (all but the time of the Heptarchie) ſtood ſelfelie-Monarchike, and in paragon with either <hi>Fraunce</hi> or <hi>Spaine,</hi> and other the greateſt Monarchies of chriſtendome as well for the honours of warre as of peace: a nation which hath twice conquered <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and as for <hi>Spaine,</hi> was able to free her neck from the Daniſh yoke (the Dane being a nation full of valour) within one 24. yeeres, the Spaniard not perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming his like freedome from the Moore (being a baſe and obſcure nation) vnder 700: a nation which was able to bring in a Dolphin of <hi>Fraunce</hi> with all the martiall-flower of that kingdome to make vſe of here at home euen in ciuill warres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelues, and that done ſafelie to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite it ſelfe againe of him &amp; them, which what nation in chriſtendome but <hi>England</hi> would haue aduentured? a nation whoſe Empire hath exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the Ile of <hi>Thule</hi> to the <hi>Pirenean</hi>-mounts
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:178002:25"/> 
               <hi>ſimul &amp; ſemel,</hi> and that in ſetled peace, as we may read in the raigne of king <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſecond: a nation which hath beene able to ſend forth ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and <hi>Armadoes</hi> as farre as the holie land, and performed more ſeruice for God and his church there then any other, nay then all other chriſtian people concurring in the ſame: a nation that hath made other countries both afraid and beholding to it, and as we read great Princes, yea and an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour her Penſioners: a nation that hath fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht Saint <hi>Peters</hi> ſea with two excellent good Popes, and the Catholicke church with as manie Saints and deepe learned men (and at this day doth) as anie countrie in chriſtendome beſides, it being the firſt begotten childe of the ſame, &amp; our Ladies Dowre: briefe, a nation which at this day euen vnder a woman, and (as the Spaniard and Ieſuits pretend in her vniuſt vndertakings) hath hitherto bin able to make her partie good againſt all the world, maintaining it ſelfe in peace when all her neighbour-ſtates round about her are on fire: ſuch a nation (I ſay) to ceaſe now at length her Monarchicke-honour, and become vaſſall to <hi>Spaine</hi> or any nation in the world be it by title or conqueſt, or whatſoeuer pretence, yea of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; oh how diſhonourable and abominable were it to true Engliſh-nature and valour, and ſcandalous to all the world.</p>
            <p>Prouinciall (I ſay) for ſo ſhould it be were it either vnder the brother or the ſiſter of <hi>Spaine,</hi> ſeeing that neither of their ſtates <hi>Spaine</hi> or <hi>Flaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> would agree his or her throne to be out of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:178002:25"/> them, and (in faith) for <hi>England</hi> to be ruled by a Prince out of the land (which neuer yet was ſeene ſince <hi>England</hi> was <hi>England</hi>) as little reaſon it hath as well for her profit, as for her honour. If in <hi>Spaine,</hi> it is too farre off; if in <hi>Flaunders,</hi> neither yet is that neere enough: beſides, that all thoſe Prouinces make but an Archduke, which is farre vnder the honour of a realme ſuch as <hi>England</hi> is, whoſe Crowne is, and euer was Emperiall, both for waight and faſhion. Then to be gouerned by their deputies, ſay vice-royes (which the <hi>Infanta</hi> cannot afford being her ſelfe no Queene) how diſpleaſing that were on the otherſide the cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of <hi>Flaunders</hi> may any time theſe 30. yeers, and yet at this day teach vs. For what cutting off of the Nobilitie of the land, came in with the Duke of <hi>Alua,</hi> and what oppreſſion of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and with and for them both, what warres and waſte of thoſe eſtates to this houre? The like perhaps may be alleaged of Ireland vnder her Maieſties deputies (at leaſt the Iriſhrie ſo pretend) iuſtifiying their preſent rebellion vpon their harſh hand ouer them; though (queſtionles) here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they haue little reaſon, but rather doe bite and whine at once, &amp; are turnd rebels for not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their ſauagerie when they are well, who were it Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes (how ere they here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with pretend religion) as little would they be loyall. They want but to haue taſted the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard a while to become true againe to <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Infantaes</hi> eſtate here (if of the two that be it the Ieſuits had rather, and that withall her
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:178002:26"/> own countrie would aſſent to her reſidence here) beſides the abſurdities and inconueniences here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of alreadie cited this is another, and not the leaſt (to wit) the vnlikelihood of her euer hauing iſſue, being iſſue-leſſe at theſe yeeres, whereby would remaine the ſame vncertaintie of an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh heire after her that now is. In lieu whereof, what factions were it not likelie ſhee would du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her raigne ouer vs maintaine for her bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; his heires ſucceſſion to the Crowne? what ielouſies? nay perhaps what not ciuil wars? ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a partie alreadie aggreeued for the ſuppoſed wrongs done by <hi>England</hi> both to her father and her brother, for which ſhe would happilie thinke by this meanes to make them full amends, or at leaſt if ſuch her practiſe ſhould not preuaile, to ſhew her ſelfe in ſo aſſaying a verie louing ſiſter. It is not her laying open her Low-countries, and her brothers dominions, no not his Indies to our trafficke in the meane time (which aſwell is like to come to paſſe ere long (God willing) through their inforced amitie with vs) can counteruaile this hazard alone, muchleſſe all the aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Nor is it yet halfe an age, ſince the Spaniſh na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being admitted into our countrie in al loue, and in the greateſt knot of amitie that may be i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined (to wit) by the mariage of their Prince with ours, at what time and that in how ſhort a time, we were as willing to be rid of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (through their ill deſeruings) as ſome of our countrie men with the loſſe of their liues ſhewed themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>little afore vnwilling of their comming, we may
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:178002:26"/> yet verie well remember. We may yet very well remember the chargeable vſe they then made of our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try in their own wars both by land &amp; ſea, &amp; our loſſe of <hi>Caleis</hi> the while. We may yet reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber their inſolence amongſt vs, &amp; proude miſgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernance to the contempt of our nobilitie, much more of our commons; for which no ſooner was that knot between the two nations broken by the death of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bleſſed Queene, but ſtraight they were made to know how great diſguſt they had giuen vs, with the loſſe of ſome of their liues for a fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well. If then comming in as friends, they deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as foes at our countries hands; how much more comming in as foes (though nere ſomuch vnder the couert of religious friends) may wee thinke to find them cruell and tyrannous, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie hauing had ſince, ſo much matter of reuenge miniſtred them from hence as they aſſume? Or why did they not then (if their title were ſuch to the Crowne of <hi>England</hi> as the Ieſuits ſuggeſt) make vſe of that oportunitie for their ſubiecting vs? But (ſure) it ſeemes twas not the will of God, both for that they tooke no ſuch counſaile then, and alſo (if they meant anie ſuch matter) Gods ſequeſtring the Spaniſh Prince from out the realme, and taking away the Queene all at one time. Nay more, to note the will of God in this behalfe, he alſo tooke away the iſſue he had (as I haue crediblie heard) by our Queene; as it were to ſhew that hee would not haue <hi>England</hi> anie way Spaniſh, though <hi>England</hi> it ſelfe neuer ſo faine would. Great and ample dowre he likewiſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:178002:27"/> laid vnto <hi>Englands</hi> crowne by the match, and yet it was not Gods will that all that ſhould winne <hi>England</hi> Spaniſh. How much more may we then hope in God neuer to ſee it ſuch by being laid to <hi>Spaine,</hi> eſpeciallie ſo baſelie and abiectlie as theſe hot-ſpurre Fathers would haue it; ſeeing that <hi>Spaine</hi> laid to it in ſo wooing wiſe could not make it Spaniſh.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, what reaſon were it that <hi>Spaine</hi> ſhould be ſo great aboue all her neighbours, as by the poſſeſſing of <hi>England?</hi> nay, what preiudice were it not to all chriſtendome, conſidering the proude and tyrannous humour of that nation? Say that we for our parts ſhould haue Catholicke religion by the meanes, &amp; with it peace and traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficke with all chriſtendome, and all chriſtendome the ſame with vs; and perhaps all chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces peace with one another too, which by our practiſes (ſay the Ieſuits) hath bin, and daylie is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringed. Graunt we all this, doth it therefore fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that <hi>Spaine</hi> is ſure to haue euer a good king o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer her, to adminiſter ſuch her greatneſſe in good manner? yea, is <hi>Spaine</hi> euer ſure of a Catholicke king vnder whom to continue Catholicke it ſelf, and all her eſtates vnder her? In the fiue &amp; twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth yeere of the raigne of our Soueraigne Lord and King <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight, Catholicke religion was as vnlikely to haue bin ſuppreſt in <hi>England,</hi> as it is at this day in <hi>Spaine</hi> vnder <hi>Philip</hi> the third, and yet (we ſee) how ſoone after it followed, and what it is now come to. The like may chaunce to <hi>Spaine</hi> vnder a king according: and by the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:178002:27"/> ſame reaſon why may not wee alſo hope for Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke religion yet once againe here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as they not expect the Proteſtant? it being no more impoſſible, nay more probable for a Proteſtant-Prince to returne Catholicke, ſeeing that <hi>magna eſt veritas &amp; praualet,</hi> then for a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke one to turne Proteſtant, it being too true that <hi>ruimus in vetitum ſemper, cupimuſque negata.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſay that <hi>Spaine</hi> ſhould be ſo fortunate in her Soueraignes as to haue them euer Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke, whereby Catholicke religion ſtill to flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in their dominions; yet neither doth that take away all other miſchiefes which may follow of their greatnes, as breach with their neighbour-Princes, and ſo warres abroad (and be but for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of ſuch ſpirits as happilie would elſe through peace be tumultuous at home) &amp; conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently oppreſſion of their ſubiects for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of thoſe warres, eſpeciallie their ſubiects lying ſo farre off as <hi>England,</hi> &amp; gouerned by their deputies, together with a thouſand ſuch like miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes which are incident to great Monarches as from their greatnes, and hauing more then they can well weld though nere ſo Catholicke and good otherwiſe. And if it be ſo (as the Ieſuits ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniate) that <hi>England</hi> alone troubles all the world, how much more (trow yee) would all the world be troubled, were <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>England</hi> one vnder a quarrellous Prince? or rather how would not <hi>England</hi> then haue her part of troubles with all the world which now is quiet? Great are the hazards that are from greateſt Monarches
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:178002:28"/> both to the Church and the ciuill ſtate of the world, for that their taking to be bad (as moſt men are naturallie ſo inclinde, eſpeciallie when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue controule) carries all in like manner with them, making their greatneſſe the counterpoiſe, or ouer-biaſſe to goodneſſe, as wee read in the Greeke Emperours, whoſe aptneſſe to hereſie wrought continuall ſchiſmes in the church, till in the end God gaue that Empire with her Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour ouer for the ſame to the Turke, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. So likewiſe afore them, the Romaine Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, who being manie bad to one good, what diſorder wrought not their example, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie throughout all their Empire? for which it pleaſed God at laſt to diſſolue it, and conuert it into manie kingdomes and Prouinces as now we ſee it; whereby though one ſtate or kingdome ſhould miſcarie vnder an vnhappie Prince, yet the reſt may tarrie good and proſperous.</p>
            <p>If then ſuch hath bin the prouidence of God, to depoſe the Romaine Empire from her great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes for her ſinnes as from her greatnes, and hath diſpoſd it into diſtinct ſtates and Prouinces as in reformation; why then doe the Ieſuits ſo labour to erect a Spaniſh Empire againſt ſuch the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God for the euils hee ſaw in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine? or rather why not let <hi>England</hi> continue Engliſh, and worke it ſelfe Catholicke againe (if it pleaſe God) in Engliſh manner? Are they ſo much of God almighties counſaile, as to know whether is more to his honour, the proceeding practiſe of the Seminaries (as hitherto) for the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:178002:28"/> good of his church and our countrie, or the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſword? Or rather what chriſtian ſpirit is not able to diſtinguiſh whether of the two is more perfect? and how little behoofefull, nay how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull is the drumme and enſigne where the word is likelie to ſpeed, as here amongſt vs it day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie makes faire ſhew to doe. Briefe; a Heathen man could ſee it to be better, and ſay thereupon: <hi>Cedant arma togae, concedant laurea linguae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which ſuch their Spaniſh raigne if it ſhould once come to paſſe in our countrie (as I beſeech God I may neuer ſee it either with or againſt our wils) how hard, yea impoſſible a matter it were to euict that nation out againe, <hi>Sicilie, Naples, Lumbardie,</hi> and the greater part of the Low-countries doth at this day teach vs by their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable, &amp; extreame bondage; not that <hi>Spaines</hi> valour maintaines ſuch her dominion ouer them, but her Indies. Moſt of all abſurd therefore it is to thinke it likelie, that which Father <hi>Cowbucke</hi> by his papers &amp; agents ſo labours to perſwade <hi>(viz.)</hi> that of their owne good nature they wil ſelfelie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide the realme, after hauing once eſtabliſht the Catholicke religion in it, which (ſaith hee) is all that the Catholicke king deſires. Oh vnſauorie aſſertion, &amp; arguing rather that ſimplicitie which ought to be in a religious perſon, then the ſubtilty that is in him. As though if a reconciled foe be neuer to be throughlie affied; a preſent enimie for pretended wrongs, and who daylie ſeekes and aſſayes to be reuenged, may hauing once the law in his own hand) be ſo farre forth truſted as with
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:178002:29"/> a kingdome; ſeeing that for it what faith, what iuſtice euer tooke place in this world? Or as though the pretence to continue our ſaid holie religion amongſt vs, may not as ſtronglie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him (were religion his meere motiue) to ſettle in this land, as to come to inueſt the ſame.</p>
            <p>Oh (coſin) ſhew yee me where euer religion and armes marcht ſo together; ſhew ye me where euer ye read of a Prince that vanquiſhing a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie by the ſword, euer left it but ſo; which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly is no leauings but loſſe. Eſpecially a crowne ſo ſweet and ſo hard to winne as <hi>Englands,</hi> is it likelie the Spaniard would not eſteeme it worth the holding? or leaue ſuch a realme as this to it ſelfe, contenting him onelie to haue it to friend when he may enioy it ſubiect? Belieue me (coſin) they are no ſuch <hi>Aeſops</hi> coxcombs, as finding ſo rich a iewell as <hi>England,</hi> to leaue it as a thing of nought; they hauing vſde the Indies long, and being better iewellers then ſo: nor are they ſo te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate a people, neither yet is <hi>Spaine</hi> ſo much the Paradice of the world (it being for the moſt part a verie barren and deſert ſoyle) that they ſhould hold <hi>England</hi> ſo little worth as not worth the hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. If <hi>Englands</hi> amitie heretofore with <hi>Spaine</hi> haue not deſerued a worthier opinion at her hands then ſo; at leaſt her late enmitie hath: du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which what boote we haue made of it both by land and by ſea all the world knowes; what it of vs it may put it in her eye. Beſides, the deere proffer the Spaniard made for <hi>England</hi> as <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as well as for reuenge in 88. with the loſſe
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:178002:29"/> both of their honours and liues, and the infinite charges of their <hi>Armado,</hi> ſhewes plainelie at what price they were willing to haue purchaſte it, at a leſſe then which it is not likelie that they would euer haue left it. Tuſh tuſh, it is verie well knowne that the Spaniard ſo eſteemes of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that not being able to make it Spaniſh, hee could be content that euen <hi>Spaine</hi> were Engliſh, for ſome, yea ſundrie honours which it hath, and <hi>Spaine</hi> wants. At leaſt their wiſe and valo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous king the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> ſo eſteemed of <hi>England,</hi> that in his precepts to his ſonne the laſt <hi>Phillip</hi> on his death-bed, hee ſtucke not to make this one, and that the greateſt earthlie one vnto him in theſe words. And (ſonne) in briefe; <hi>Paz con Yngalatierra, y guerra con todo el mondo;</hi> as much to ſay as; Sonne, be at peace with <hi>England,</hi> and warre with all the world. How baſe were it then in vs to diſeſteeme our nation ſo, as to wiſh it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der another, which ſo highlie, ſo noble an Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour commended? and which the Ieſuits them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues finde to flow with milke and honie vnto them, euen vnder perſecution? There is no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion but greatlie may religion ſway a Prince, but yet not ſo as to leaue a Crowne. We reade of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie that haue tranſgreſt, yea, left all religion for a Crowne, but of verie few that euer left a Crowne for religion. Yea, moſt Princes hold it a point of religion, neuer to leaue a Crowne till a Crowne leaue them.</p>
            <p>See then (I pray) how ſillie an Oratour father <hi>Cowbucke</hi> is in this his gentle perſwaſion of the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:178002:30"/> Spaniard, and how vngentle a minde he beares to his countrie (being indeed no gentleman) and laſtlie (ſomewhat to excuſe the man) how well it ſteeds him to ſeeme the religious in this Paradox for his credits ſake, though thereby hee diſcredit his religion in but ſeeming ſo. Neither for your credit-ſake (coſin) will I anie further perſwade you herein, leaſt in ſo ſeeming to vnder-value your iudgement in a cleare caſe, I ſhould ſeeme not onlie the diſcurteous vnto you, but alſo vnci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. For, what generous nature in the world would endure his countrie to be conquered by ſtraungers? or what ſot imagine in a conquerour a voluntarie abandon of a Crowne, ſeeing that in ſuch a caſe aboue all other worldly caſes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, <hi>Non minor eſt virtus quàm quaerere, parta tenere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Paſſing politickelie notwithſtanding deales the king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> ſeeing his right to this realme and his ſucceſſes of warre for the ſame haue hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto bin no better, to entertaine religious men in the purſuite thereof; for that it is much what a religious perſon once turnd politicke may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade with the vulgar, making pure religion and deuotion his colours, then which no Oratorie can ſo enueigle affections not onely to couet, but alſo to vndertake matter euen againſt nature. And on the other ſide, too cheape were <hi>England</hi> wonne to <hi>Spaine</hi> with ſo piping: neither need the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> greatlie repine at the few Caricks, and townes wee haue taken and ſpoiled of his; neither yet at his Catholicke charges in maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:178002:30"/> two Engliſhe Seminaries at this day to our Church in his countrie, if he can carue himſelfe ſo eaſie and ſo ample amends: Which (as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Seminaries <hi>quatinùs</hi> vnder Ieſuits diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline) and alſo his foreſaid <hi>Armado</hi> of 88. if his charitie be ſo great toward vs, or rather not his ambition (for before the miſcarriage of that <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mado</hi> on our coſt thoſe Seminaries were not ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in <hi>Spaine,</hi> but ſince) are there not (I pray) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kingdomes aſwell as <hi>England,</hi> vpon which he may likewiſe practiſe ſuch his <hi>Armadoes</hi> firſt, and then after alſo erect them the like Seminaries, namelie with Ieſuit-ſuperiours ouer them; which if the one were without the other, or that the Seminaries had beene erected before the <hi>Arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> were no ſuch ſuſpitious dealing, but (truely) very faire and friendly play like to the laſt French kings in that of <hi>Rhemes;</hi> but as thus <hi>England</hi> may well ſay. <hi>Timeo Danaos &amp; dona ferentes;</hi> and the rather for that father <hi>Cowbucke</hi> hath of late gotten diuers of the youths hands of thoſe Seminaries to the Ladie <hi>Infantaes</hi> title (as wee heare) which (alaſſe poore man) wil neuer earne him the price of a Cardinals hat, much leſſe the honor to weare it.</p>
            <p>But (as I ſay) if the king of <hi>Spaines</hi> zeale be ſuch as needs he will be doing; why there is <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> two ample kingdomes both hereticall; why hath he no Ieſuits there, or why ſends he no <hi>Armadoes</hi> thether? Oh (belike) he ſees that they haue kings to defend them, and <hi>England</hi> but a Queene, but a woman; whom
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:178002:31"/> (hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily) being ſuch, he would haue the world thinke he came a wooing vnto that yeere: which (true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie) beſides the manner being ſo martiall, was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vnlawfull in the maine; ſeeing it is not allowa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for any Catholike, much leſſe the Catholicke king, the king of Catholickes to marrie two ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters (though the one were Catholicke) without diſpenſation, much leſſe perforce. Or if hee will ſay that not thoſe kingdomes but <hi>England</hi> hath wronged him, what is that (I pray) for Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh-men to betray therefore their countrie vnto him? or why ſhould not wee the rather for that reaſon ſuſpect his pretence of religion in his comming? Shall the ſonne becauſe the father hath done his neighbour wrong, ioyne with that neighbour to cut his fathers throat? God defend: or were it religion or moralitie in that neighbour to make ſuch vſe of the ſonne? truelie no. And yet ſuch is <hi>Spaines</hi> dealing with our countrie and vs at this day, and ſo good Caſuiſts are Ieſuits.</p>
            <p>Graunt wee (as the Ieſuits ſuggeſt) that our countrie hath and doth maintaine <hi>Spaines</hi> rebels againſt her, ſackt her townes, inuaded her treſures both by ſea and land; yet were it ſo, and that it became ſubiects to define their Soueraignes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of ſtate; all that an Engliſh-Catholicke man might doe in this caſe, is but to be ſorrie at the iniuſtice, &amp; rather abide the fortune of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie for the fault (what God ſhall award) then be a traitour to it therefore; and it is innocence e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in him not to be guiltie of his countries ſinne, howſoeuer hee rue it in her ſhame. And
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:178002:31"/> who can tell whether happilie the next age may raiſe vp an Engliſh Soueraigne whoſe amity with <hi>Spaine</hi> may more auaile <hi>Spaine,</hi> then theſe preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded domages come to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> At leaſt wiſe Chronicles doe tell, how that <hi>Spaine</hi> hath of auncientie more then once or twice beene beholding to Engliſh fauours farre aboue theſe treſpaſſes, which we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer read it requited yet, till now that <hi>England</hi> payes it ſelfe. All the requitall that may be ſo tearmed is the two Seminaries which at this day it maintaines to our Church (as aforeſaid) if at leaſt he diſparage it not with an vſurping intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereof the <hi>Armado</hi> of 88. and the Ieſuits practiſes (whom he hath deputed ouer thoſe Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries) make too palpable ſhew. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer theſe his Seminaries may be thought re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitals to <hi>Englands</hi> former fauours; ſure I am they are no benefits ſo of worth, as for which Engliſh Catholickes ſhould be traitours to their Prince and countrie in <hi>Spaines</hi> behalfe: much leſſe the kings penſions to our people in his dominions, which being greater in title the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are in truth, I do not ſee but their farre ſleighter ſeruices may deſerue them then the ſale of their deere coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and their honours.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake this by proofe (good coſin) both in my ſelfe (as you know) and too manie my good friends that yet are in his, and his ſiſters ſeruice; the more was my fault when as it was, though therby the more my experience in diſlike of that nation. Furthermore, thus much I aſſure yee of my certaine knowledge, that in the action of 88.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:178002:32"/> againſt our countrie, the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> made no ſuch ſhew or countenance to our nation then ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him in his armie in the Low-countries, as alſo in the <hi>Armado,</hi> as to make vs thinke, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee came either in loue or religion againſt it (as the Ieſuits here ſuggeſt both in that and in the next pretended) but the cleane contrarie, that is, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge and rapine. For, beſides that neither in the one, nor in the other there was anie Briefe of his holines promulged, ne (as afore is ſhowne) ought to haue beene promulged in allowance of that action, whereby the Catholicke-ſubiects of this land to haue beene bound to concurre thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; the Spaniard in ech part notoriouſlie deſerud the cleane contrarie at our hands. My eye was a witneſſe of a notable affront done by a Spaniſh captaine vnto my Lord of <hi>Westmerland</hi> in <hi>Bruges,</hi> at the verie inſtant of the <hi>Armadoes</hi> being on our coaſt (the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> then lying with all his Court there, and his Campe there abouts) name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, vpon his ſhew of diſguſt that he was no more regarded, the ſeruice being for his countrie.</p>
            <p>In like manner did I not then ſee after our fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Spaniſh-fleet in the narrow ſeas, the young Prince of <hi>Aſcoli</hi> at his fugitiue-arriuall to <hi>Dunkerke</hi> the morrow after, where the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> entertained him on the ſtrond; him (I ſay) in anſwere to the Dukes queſtion what newes of the <hi>Armado</hi> vncap himſelfe, and grinning toward heauen ſweare by it, that he thought not onlie all the foure elements were <hi>Lutherans</hi> that night and all that morning, but alſo God himſelfe; ſo blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:178002:32"/> was his Spaniſh-ſpirit, much leſſe religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as to come to conquer a countrie for religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Better yet of the two, &amp; merrier was the Duke of <hi>Oſſuna</hi> (who at this preſent ſerues the <hi>Infanta</hi> before <hi>Oſtend</hi>) his repreſentation, and anſwere to the then king of <hi>Spaine</hi> within a while after; who being the firſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that arriued at the Court with the ſucceſſeles newes of the <hi>Armado,</hi> ſtucke a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaffe at his ſide, &amp; a ſpindle at his backe in ſteede of rapier and dagger, and ſo ſhewd himſelfe to the king while he was at Maſſe. Whom the king after Maſſe asking what ſucceſſe God had ſent, he merrilie pointed his maieſtie to thoſe his armes, ſaying and ſwearing that ſince they had fought ſo woman-like, and that a woman had foiled them, they were worthy before God and man to weare from thence forth none other. Whereupon the king haſtilie ſtept to the altar, and taking a ſiluer candleſticke from off the ſame, ſwore a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous oth that he would waſte not only al <hi>Spaine,</hi> but alſo all his Indies to that candleſticke, but he would be auenged of <hi>England;</hi> ſuch was the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke-kings religion (forſooth) toward our countrie, or rather his prophane ambition &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite: for which it hath pleaſed God (who ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther allowes conqueſts for religion, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the ſucceſſes wars of Chriſtians in the Holie-land of yoare, much leſſe for meere ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) to ſpeed his two like attempts ſince as bad as that firſt. This latter newes of <hi>Oſſuna</hi> in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſaid, came reported into the Low-countries
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:178002:33"/> from the Court of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and confirmed by ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie letters to gentlemen in the Spaniſh regiment where I then ſerued.</p>
            <p>I will not tell yee (for I cannot) how many vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifts came to the Duke of <hi>Parmaes</hi> campe from out all the Prouinces of Chriſtendome, in hope and vaunt to make themſelues whole by <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> what waging for our noblemens heads; what queſtioning Sir <hi>William Stanlies</hi> ſouldiers where the riches of our countrie moſt lay; what luſt after our women-kind, yea our Ladies by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie raskall ſouldier; and what villanie not? I ſaw and heard all this (coſin) and a great deale more, and worſe, and therefore I may ſafelie ſay it and ſweare it for a certaine vnto you. Moreouer, to confirme this aſſertion of Spaniſh-impietie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward our countrie, I will giue you a Flemmiſh inſtant for the ſame. My father was the man whom I haue often heard tell, how that the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row after the Spaniards entring the towne of <hi>Maſtreicht</hi> in <hi>Brabrant</hi> by aſſault, hee there ſaw in cold blood a Spaniſh ſouldier, to whom a poore Burgar of the towne came ſuppliant on his knees in the open ſtreet, and beſought him for his life, proteſting that hee euer was a Catholicke from his cradle, the ſaid wretched Spaniard to murder him neuertheleſſe, ſaying: oh Flemming, then wil thy ſoule goe the white way, and much good may it doe thee.</p>
            <p>I conclude then, that if the Spaniard be ſuch toward Flemmiſh Catholickes, &amp; alſo no kinder (then is ſaid) toward Engliſh as yet in the purſute
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:178002:33"/> of his dominion ouer vs (when in all wiſedome he ſhould vſe vs moſt benignelie, though but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblingly, whereby the rather to vvin our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, vvhich is the eaſieſt and ſureſt conqueſt of all other) vvhat other may both Proteſtant and Catholicke expect at his hands here in <hi>England</hi> another day vpon his atchieueme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by armes? No leſſe vnworthilie haue the Ieſuits carried them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in thoſe parts, and elſ-where in the kings dominions toward our gentlemen, doing them ſo many indignities and diſguſts as I ſhame to tel, though meete they vvere to be knowne in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our gentlemens patiences, as vvell there as here at home for the Catholicke cauſe. Onlie here and there a skip-lack they haue aduanced to fodder and cloathes ſcarſe competent, for being their obſequious Implements in whatſoeuer diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyaltie they vvould employ them againſt their countrie, vvhiles gentlemen of eſtimable parts they haue miſregarded, yea diſcarded for being more loyall. In vaine therefore doe the Ieſuits perſwade vs the king of <hi>Spaines</hi> honourable vſage of our nation after a conqueſt, who together with them afore the ſame entreat it ſo diſhonourablie: and more then vaine, yea accurſed vvere vvee to be ſo caught vvith their pipe (as they pretend of grace) as to incurre miſ-nature.</p>
            <p>Stand vve (coſin) ſtand we that are <hi>Englands</hi> vpon Engliſh, and let all forraine rule goe by: ſtand vve vpon the expreſſe Statute of our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie (being Catholicke) inhibiting all forraine temporall iuriſdiction vvithin the ſame. Stand
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:178002:34"/> vve againſt, yea ſtronglie withſtand vve Fa. <hi>Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bucke</hi> and his Societies vnnatural practiſes in Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh behalfe, and vvhatſoeuer forraine nations al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie <hi>Armadoes,</hi> remembring ſtil that <hi>facilius eſt excludere quàm expellere:</hi> and alſo ſtill remembring how if the Catholicke church haue condemned the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> of old, and the <hi>Caluiniſts</hi> of late in <hi>Fraunce;</hi> the monocular-Taborite <hi>Ziſca</hi> in <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia; Iohn</hi> of <hi>Leyden,</hi> &amp; <hi>Th. Muncer</hi> in <hi>Germanie,</hi> and others elſ-where, as vvell for managing reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion by armes, as for heretickes; how much leſſe lawfull it is in the Catholicke king (being a child of the church) ſo to doe: and hovv verie <hi>Zuingli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> the Ieſuits are that thus preach Chriſt vnto vs vvith a Bible in one hand, and a ſword in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: laſtlie remembring ſtill the honour and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a Patriot, the honours of our forefathers, and ſingularlie the honours of this our deere countrie <hi>England.</hi> I, I, let euerie cup haue his owne couer, and euerie countrie his owne king. I vvater were good to drinke with wine (quoth a good fellow) God himſelfe would haue put it into the grape; but euerie ſimple is beſt. And far more Catholicke, and farre more naturall it is, to hope one day to be beholding to our owne State for Catholicke libertie, then to a forraine, vvith ſo deſperate conditions and againſt all reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. If we our ſelues vvithin our ſelues baniſht religion, vvhy may not wee our ſelues within our ſelues bring it in againe, the Proteſtant novv be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no more vnlikely to be auoided, then the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke then was. I meane (if it ſo pleaſe her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie)
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:178002:34"/> or at leaſt but to tolerate it, which as vvell here as in <hi>Fraunce</hi> and other neighbour-States, might vvell ſtand vvith that in requeſt vvithout hazard, yea vvith ſecuritie to her royall perſon and eſtate.</p>
            <p>But this is a point meerelie in her Maieſties grace to complie vvithall, and to too happy for vs to be eaſilie expected at her hands, conſidering her Highneſſe inurd diſpleaſure vvith the Sea-A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicke euen <hi>ab incunabulis;</hi> alſo ſince, for the Buls aforeſaid; and novv laſtlie and that daylie, for the diſloyall practiſes of the Ieſuits againſt her eſtate, vvhich vvee all rue vvithout difference. Hard it vvere (I ſay) for vs to hope for ſo happie a day, conſidering alſo hovv all the three eſtates of the realme are ingaged in the contrarie, and all the lawes of the land ſtand expreſſelie oppoſite and penall hereunto. Neuertheleſſe it doth mee good to thinke, hovv if ſuch a grace might be fall vs but euen tolerablie, and in neuer ſo meane a manner from our own naturall Soueraigne, hovv much more gratefullie and gladlier all true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes vvould accept it, then at an inuadours hands neuer ſo indulgentlie. Her Maieſtie for her owne part (doubtles) is paſſing meeke and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, both in reſpect of her ſex, and now her vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable age, that had not diſloyall practiſes diſpleaſ'd her, 'twas poſſible inough that her condeſcent might haue beene ſo benigne vnto vs long agoe; the rather remembring hovv heartilie her High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vvas applauded to her Crovvne at the firſt by Catholickes, and the ſame ſet vpon her Royall
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:178002:35"/> head, not by a Proteſtant but a Catholicke Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, her Maieſtie hath a wiſe Councell vvhich cannot but ſee, that though for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time the eſtates eccleſiaſticall and ciuill both of our countrie being ſo throughly ſetled as they are, it is meete (they thinke) and eaſie (we know) to keepe the Catholicke vnder and ſuppreſt, yet what hereafter in a chaunge, and in a troubled State our partie may work it ſelfe, they may rather perhaps gueſſe, then preuent. Sure I am wee are not ſo ignoble a partie in the land for all the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution theſe fortie yeeres, but that the vnitie thereof vvith the reſt at ſuch a day will perhaps be as requiſite for our common-weale as any other. The conſideration vvherof, together with others no leſſe important may ſomewhat preuaile with ſo prudent a Councell as her Maieſties is, if not for a toleration of our rites, at leaſt a mitigation of our aggriefes in the meane time, and the rather for that <hi>ſufficit diei malitia ſua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Howſouer, this likelihood wee haue of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like religion yet once againe in our countrie by our owne, not forraine; neither yet warlike but peacefull and euen voluntarie meanes, in that both Engliſh Saints-ſeed is plentifullie ſowne for it anie time theſe fortie yeeres, and alſo manie Conuertites come in daylie, and out of queſtion infinite more would, were it not that <hi>Leo eſt in via (viz)</hi> the penall lawes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land. But what is that to the will of a Prince? or vvhat Princes heart is not in the hand of God? Who erected all of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:178002:35"/> can he not tranſlate any thing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Can he not conuert the inſtruments of his anger, yea malice it ſelfe to grace, and to his honour if hee pleaſe? It is neither the archers hand, nor yet the aime gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, but God alonelie that directs the arrow where to light; not but what they doe is their deed neuertheleſſe. I ſay thus much (coſin) by what wee haue ſeene of late hapned in our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie in fauour of the Catholicke faith euen by the Proteſtants hand, in ſuppreſſing (though not in that ſenſe) the great Puritan-partie, being the greateſt enimie to our Holies of all the hereſies in this land. For which great pittie it was, ſo noble a ſubiect as the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and with him ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie worthie gentlemen to be made vſe of by it in his diſcontents to the end wee ſaw. Such ſpirit haue Puritanes, &amp; ſo vnfortunate vvas that poore Earle: and namelie ſo vnfortunate thoſe few Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes that of ignorance (I dare ſweare) of his proiect ſtucke to him in thoſe ſuds. Had her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Catholicke-ſubiects but a quater the grace that Puritanes haue in this realme, yea but her bare conniuence, I aſſure mee their gratitude would not be ſo pure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but pure in deed; they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo loyall as they are (ſetting Ieſuits aſide) euen vnder her frowne.</p>
            <p>And as for her Highneſſe after ſo manie tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphes ouer both her couert and ouert enimies, fairelie (me thinks) vvith her royall honour it may ſtand vvhat euen novv I touched of a religious-toleration to vs her poore Catholicke ſubiects; ſeeing that verie proper it is to a Lyons noble na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:178002:36"/> as well <hi>parcere ſubiectis,</hi> as, <hi>dobellare ſuperbos.</hi> Hauing hitherto done and daylie doing the latter (thorough Gods ſecret iudgements) to doe the other now can no waies ſeeme in her of force or feare. Wherein notwithſtanding if her High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe pleaſe not to be ſo indulgent Princeſſe vnto vs, and that our prayers are not yet worthie to be ſo farre forth heard of God (through the ill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruings of the Ieſuits in our church, and at her Maieſties hands) what part and portion of dutie remaines vnto vs other then that we haue hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to performed? <hi>(viz)</hi> ſtill our inſtant prayers to God for it, and for want of it Patience, knowing that <hi>In patientia poſſidebimus animas nostras:</hi> alſo continuance of paſſiue-fortitude being willed to be <hi>Fortes in bello,</hi> &amp; not to feare thoſe <hi>qui occidunt corpus, anima autem non habent potestatem:</hi> likewiſe of Perſeuerance, ſeeing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>qui perſeuerauerit vſque in finem ſaluus erit:</hi> and laſtlie, and ſtill betweene of Hope, for that <hi>ſpes non confundit.</hi> This (coſin) is true Catholicke religion in this caſe, and true Engliſh nature and valour, true faith, &amp; true cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie: and what the Ieſuits perſwade vs toward a conqueſt of our deere countrie vpon pretence of nere ſo much pietie, were abominable diſloyaltie in vs to our Prince; and alſo baſe puſillanimitie and diffidence in God, wee to concurre there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            <p>No no, a State ſo ſetled as this vnder a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe ſo magnanimious, ſo mightie, ſo fortunate, is not likelie to be altered in our fauours by Ieſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall and Spaniſh-braues; but contrariwiſe by
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:178002:36"/> our humble ſutes, ſeruices, ſubmiſſion and meeke deſerts. Thus and no otherwiſe muſt we hope to incline her Maieſtie, and the State to fauour vs, if not for our religion-ſake, at leaſt for our loyalties: and (pleaſe God) the Popes holines and the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> would heretofore or yet would ſeeke to winne her Maieſtie, both to them and vs by faire meanes, rather then by ſoule, a courſe which was yet neuer taken. My Lord of <hi>Durham</hi> this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-time made a Sermon at Paules croſſe (as I heard) againſt a toleration to vs by the ſtate; I pray God incline his Lordſhips heart, &amp; the reſt of his ranke, and generallie all the realme to a more moderation. Of as hard beginning as this hath often-times through Gods goodnes ſorted a faire end, and ſo there may of this if Catholicks can but diſ-Ieſuit themſelues now another while toward the State, and ſeeke to be beholding ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to it then to <hi>Spaine,</hi> which latter cannot (out of doubt) be but with vtter misfortune to our countrie. And why ſhould not wee the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes of <hi>England</hi> ſute our fidelities and loue (I ſay not our religion) to our Proteſtant-Princeſſe, as well as the Proteſtants of <hi>Fraunce</hi> doe theirs to their Catholicke king; whereby we to enioy the ſame peace, yea fauours at her Highnes hands here, as they doe at his there? Or is it well done in them to doe ſo, and were it ill in vs? Is it either for our honour or eaſe to be in her Maieſties diſguſt, when we may ioy in her grace? Fie, that Ieſuits ſhould transforme vs into ſuch cra-fiſhes, as to make our opinions goe ſo a-skew from our beſt
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:178002:37"/> aduantages. For my owne part, I am verilie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that as the Iſraelites mutinies againſt God in the deſart did prorogue at his hands their arriuall in the Holie-land, ſo likewiſe the diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all practiſes of the Ieſuits hitherto againſt all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and nature amongſt vs, hath not only kept backe from vs all fauours at our Princes hands, but further incenſt her more againſt vs; for which I pray God forgiue and amend them. If our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ſtayed almoſt 4000. yeeres afore euer it pleaſed him to come to redeeme the world, how is it that theſe Fathers cannot haue patience with our countrie one 44. yeeres? and if alſo his redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it was by his dying, how haps it that their ſpirits are ſet ſo all vpon killing? Truelie, the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is that Chriſt was wholie for vs, and they wholie for themſelues; and all his Saints ſtood wholie on the paſſiue, theſe wholie on the actiue fortitude, or rather quarrellous actiuitie.</p>
            <p>And thus (my good coſin) to conclude my diſcourſe vpon this point, you may ſee how harſh a Societie the Ieſuits are, and how ſpeenatiuelie they runne on in their miſ-grounded conceits and purpoſes, as well in their reuenge againſt the Seminaries as aforeſaid, which they could aduiſe no fitter meanes to doe it by then by libell; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in this of State, and of our church, which (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) but by conqueſt they can ſee no other meanes to right; and therefore haue (as wee ſee) verie vertuouſlie erected an Arch-prieſt the head of their faction both touching the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, themſelues being all the braine thereof, and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:178002:37"/> he (good man) but the bare forehead. I could wiſh the Fathers not to be ouer-haſtie in encre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his faculties from Rome, till eyther they ſee another <hi>Armado</hi> readie in <hi>Spaine</hi> for our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie; or that hee can vſe theſe he hath alreadie bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then againſt his own brethren, and in mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of a libell. And as for vs (coſin) of the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, let vs as touching the preſent Schiſme, do alſo our parts aſwel as the Appeala<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts by their Appeale, to quench this fire in our church by euerie ones throwing in his paile-full of water (as by this my anſwere to you I profeſſe to doe) and as for the latter, let vs remember we are Engliſhmen, and alſo Catholicks, whereby bound to be the rather true Engliſh.</p>
            <p>Let vs remember how altogether as worthie, and as able are Engliſh-mens ſonnes to inherite and predomin <hi>England,</hi> as Spaniards <hi>Spaine;</hi> and how as hitherto <hi>England</hi> hath bin ſelfely-ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, ſo it to ſcorne to become now an adiectiue, much more a ſubiectiue to <hi>Spaine</hi> or anie other nation in the world. Alſo let vs in fauour of our countrie repute euen their Holineſſes Bulles ſo highlie tending to the ſubuerſion of our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, as ſurreptiue, and graunted forth by them as men, and not as Popes: in which reſpect an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Catholicke to go againſt them to be no more vnlawfull, then were vnlawfull the laſt Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> his warres againſt the then Pope. For, the matter being a matter of fact and not of faith, as eaſie may his holineſſe erre in his proceedings therein as any other Prince; eſpeciallie tending
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:178002:38"/> to war, and to a tradition of <hi>gentis in gentem,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto his commiſſion is ſcarſe competent (as afore is ſaid vnder correction) nor yet the holie Ghoſt to be thought therein his inſpirer; but rather (as it is plaine) ſome hot-ſpurre Ieſuits, and the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard.</p>
            <p>Such for my own part is my opinion thereof, and ſuch (I thanke God) my conſcience toward my countrie, that though it be good fiſhing (as they ſay) in a troubled water, and that my eſtate be ſuch as that to better it I need not be ſquemiſh to wet my ſelfe a little; yet rather then be ſo vn-Catholicke or vn-Engliſh, I proteſt I had rather neuer eate bit of fiſh or fleſh whiles I liue. And ſuch is alſo my opinion of you, knowing you to be a gentleman, ſuch, as though the Ieſuits haue or may ſeduce your religious nature (vnder co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of religion) in inferiour matters; yet in this ſo capitall an honour to your name and nation (I dare ſay) you will neuer forget your ſelfe. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doubt I, but wherein they haue hitherro di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayed you in the matter of the Appeale againſt the Prieſts, my loue (whereof you are and may be euer certaine) together with theſe my reaſons which you haue read will reclaime you, or elſe (truelie coſin) you doe your ſelfe a great deale more wrong then me.</p>
            <p>I haue in my loue to you already exceeded the limits of a letter, neuertheleſſe to the end that <hi>ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nariè conuerſus confirmes fratres tuos</hi> againſt theſe Fathers vnchriſtian and vnnaturall impoſtures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our church and countrie, I will ſay a little
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:178002:38"/> more vnto you of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in general, and alſo of ſome of them in eſpeciall, whereby you may the better diſcerne their vndeſerts as well of all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome as of vs here at home, whatſoeuer they ſay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues their deſeruings to be in Indie. Which foraſmuch as wee haue no authenticke credence of, eyther from the Sea Apoſtolicke, or otherwiſe ſo much as morrall, that ſuch their owne reports of their well doings there are true, I doe not ſee but the ſame are as Gerunds that want Supines, wherby their fatherhoods to ſtand to the readers curteſie to beleeue them, eſpeciallie farre trauei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers being naturallie vaine-glorious, and vaine-glorie very apt to tell a lie.</p>
            <p>A kinſman of mine of good worſhip in the North (whom you know as well as I) hath done them the honour, not onlie reſolutelie to beleeue them himſelfe, but more, to tranſlate their tre-an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuarie relations from <hi>Iaponia</hi> into our Engliſh, whereby he hath purchaſt them a good opinion amongſt manie his friends to whom he hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted the ſame; which zeale (certes) I cannot greatlie blame in the good old gentleman, he do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in a religiouſnes, and the matters tending to Catholicke-edification whether they be true or falſe. Neuertheleſſe their vanitie I cannot but condemne if they haue written ought other then truth, as (being ſuch manner of men as partlie you haue alreadie read, and now Ile ſhew you more) it is not vnlikelie but they haue done, though not in moſt, yet in manie things from thence: which alſo the rather wee haue cauſe to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:178002:39"/> ſuſpect, for that diuers other religious Orders do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing daylie their Euangelicall endeuours in thoſe Eaſt-parts as farre forth, if not farther then they, (as we may read in the hiſtorie of <hi>China</hi> and elſe where) yet they report not one word thereof, but all of their owne: which ſuch their concealing a truth importing ſo highlie Gods honour to be knowne as anie thing they doe report, is (ſure) a priuatiue lie in them; and they that will not ſticke to lie ſo, it is to be feared they wil as little doubt to tell a poſitiue &amp; a reall vntruth, if it be either for their honour or aduantage, eſpeciallie hauing (as they haue by meanes of the farre diſtance) the paſ-port of vncontroule to patronize them. And ſo (by their leaues) it is to be more then preſumed in manie things they haue done, ſo vnlikelie and incongrue are ſundrie of their relations. And yet in all the Legend of their glorious exploits in <hi>Quabucondonoes</hi> Iſland, we finde no mention of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie Ieſuit that euer offred himſelfe ſlaue to a <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nez</hi> for his tranſport ouer to that continent in zeale to preach Chriſt there, nor yet of 41. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs of them at one clap; neither yet of two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand heathen ſoules baptized by them in (I wot not) how ſhort a time: all which and a great deale more we reade of Saint <hi>Augustines</hi> Order in the <hi>Phillipines</hi> faire afore euer any Ieſuit came into the Indies.</p>
            <p>Beſides, neither is <hi>Iaponia,</hi> or other the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries of Indie where they are, ſuch as doe ſtand at this day in competence or Paragon with <hi>Spaine,</hi> as ours and other Nations here in chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:178002:39"/> doe; for which the Ieſuits ſhould there (like as here) ſow factions for Spaniſh-State; neither is it there amongſt thoſe Barbarians that they care to erect their tabernacles as here in Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, whereof they are naturals: for which (I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre) they may the rather deſerue well in <hi>Indie</hi> then in <hi>Europe,</hi> hauing there nothing to intende <hi>quae ſua ſint,</hi> but onlie <hi>quae dei,</hi> and the propagation of Chriſtian beleefe as true religious men ought. Graunt we therefore (<hi>ſaluo</hi> all exception to the vnautentickneſſe of their relations) that they are good Indians, &amp; pleaſe God they were but halfe as good Engliſh; it followes not therefore that to be true which a certaine wiſe man here amongſt vs in his vnwiſe treatie aſſeuers; that they are ſo excellent me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue all excellence, that in choiſe of our Ghoſtlie Father wee are bound if anie of them be in place to goe to them afore any other, and that (forſooth) vpon paine of a deadly ſinne. Who euer would haue thought a wiſe man though but <hi>nomine tenus,</hi> could haue beene ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie a dottard as to publiſh ſuch a tract, ſo abſurde as well in ſundrie others as in this one point in fuper-exaltation of the Ieſuits. Oh were the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits men of due modeſtie, how could they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure ſo groſſe a flatterie, it being an attribute more then meete to Chriſts vicar himſelfe. But they haue a number of ſuch od Penſionarie-ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits throughout all the parts of Chriſtendome to grace them to the people (they ſeeeming to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe their kingdome wholie of this world, which Ieſus neuer did) that oftentimes with ouer-gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:178002:40"/> them they diſgrace them: and ſo likewiſe doe the Ieſuits themſelues in ſuch their ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of ſpirit.</p>
            <p>As for exmple, is it not notable ſingularitie in them to leaue to be called after their Founders name <hi>Ignatians</hi> or <hi>Loyolians</hi> (which all other or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders are) but by the high name of Ieſus; a name which no chriſtian creature was euer yet chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (by) but (in) for reuerence ſake, but by other his Saints and ſeruants names? Alſo is it not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularitie in them, they profeſſing themſelues ſo ſingular religious, and taking vpon them the 3. vowes as farre forth as any other religious men, not to riſe at midnight to the Quire, which all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther orders doe? Alſo to goe ſo diſtinctlie habited (that is to ſay vncould) from all other religious men? likewiſe to fare ſo far more daintilie in their diet then they? And which is moſt ſingular of all, to put themſelues into the Letanies to be praide for by name afore all other orders of the church, yea, and afore <hi>Domnum Apostolicum</hi> too, whom they haue expreſſelie left out, and in his ſteed put in theſe words <hi>(viz) Vt ſocietatem nominis Ieſu,</hi> and then after, <hi>Et omnes Eccleſiasticos ordines in ſancta religione conſeruare digneris,</hi> ſo mount-God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dardian-high they are in their owne vaine-glory, and yet ſo moulhill-low in the Church, as yet not a hundred yeeres old; nor yet their Founder to be found in the calender of Saints as afore is ſaid. For which their blemiſhes and manie moe the like, yea worſe a great deale (if they did it in that humilitie) a man might well hold with ſuch
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:178002:40"/> their Petition, ſeeing indeed for to too manie not onlie their blemiſhes, but alſo their verie groſſe blots they haue great need to be prayed for afore all others, and not for their ſo excellent deſerts. They are ſo paſſing vain-glorious a Societie, that call ye it the verie <hi>Tetragrammaton</hi> of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke church, and of all the chriſtian world, I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant yee it will nere a whit offend their modeſtie or make them bluſh, ſo much haue they gotten the Indian-hue, and ſo ſingular a dottard is ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laritie.</p>
            <p>Againe, is it not ſingularitie in them (being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious) to affect rule ouer the ſccular clergie; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to bring armes and conqueſt into the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke church, ſo contrarie to all Scriptures, and the practiſe of the ſame hitherto (as afore is diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) and to that end they to manage matter of State more machiuelianlie then Machiuell him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? as appeares by their erection of the Arch-Prieſt (which is alſo a title of ſingularity they haue giuen him) and all his cariages according to them and it? In effect, ſuch ſingular perſons proued the knights of the Temple, for which God in the end gaue them ouer into a reprobate ſpirit, and ſo they ended; and ſo (I doubt me) will theſe ere long, they being little leſſe warlicke, but as verie ſingular as they. And as they are a Societie thus ſingular, and ſingularitie is the roofe of all euill; ſo haue they their roote according <hi>(viz) Radicem omnium maloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auaritiam,</hi> betwixt which two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames what <hi>medium</hi> may be expected at their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds you may imagine, &amp; in part I will ſhew you.</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:178002:41"/>
            <p>Firſt therefore, as for Auarice their other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme, you are not to meruaile greatlie thereat, both for that no vice commonlie comes alone, neither is anie vice ſubſtantiue of it ſelfe as the meaneſt vertue is, as alſo for that Pride (you know) is a riotous vice, &amp; a great ſwaggerer, and therefore requires great coſts and commings in, which but by Auarice cannot well be contriued. Pride then being to haue ſuch a prop, the Ieſuits greateſt care is how to giue it a good glaſſe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it may not appeare in them as it is in proper, but as a vertue. For, ſo haue they coloured their ſingularitie alleaging for it the Apoſtles precept, <hi>Aemulamini chariſmata meliora;</hi> wherein it cannot be denied but <hi>(Aemulamini)</hi> they vſe, yea, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-vſe howſoeuer <hi>(chariſmata)</hi> they abuſe. So likewiſe for Auarice they haue their allowance and approbation, though not from the Apoſtle, but from themſelues, &amp; no waies <hi>in ordine ad De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> as hypocriticallie they pretend all their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but <hi>veriſsimè ad daemonem (viz)</hi> herehence that they hold it lawfull, <hi>vtiſcientia in confeſsione; aliâs,</hi> to make vſe or boote of men in confeſſion, as afore is touched; and how doe they it (I pray?)</p>
            <p>Firſt and formoſt, when anie penitent by their Retriuers meanes hath made choiſe of one of them for their ghoſtlie Father, he makes it a dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie matter to exhibit himſelfe vnto him on the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, but with much ceremonie, and manie a white capo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to fore-goe the way as to the recluſd king of the <hi>Abiſsines,</hi> or rather as to <hi>volto ſanto</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:178002:41"/> in <hi>Rome,</hi> giuing the Eligent to vnderſtand how his Societie is the laſt order in holie church, and therefore by all intendment the perfecteſt; for which cauſe it hath more priuiledges and facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties indulged it from the ſea Apoſtolicke, then the Seminaries or all other religious orders whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, to communicate to their ghoſtlie child. They tell him farther (or rather to ſeeme the modeſt, cauſe it to be told him by their ſaid Retriuer) that their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to this vineyard of our church, is a ſupererogatiue office of charity in them; they not being bound thereto by expreſſe profeſſion, or as members of the Seminaries (which they are not) and therefore the rather to be welcommed and eſteemed aboue them all: that they haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie correſpondence and illumination, with &amp; from the holy ghoſt as fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Apex or Zenith ouer their heads, by meanes whereof they haue alſo (they ſay) certaine ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall ſpirituall rules and exerciſes, ouer and aboue their foreſaid externall faculties and priuiledges from <hi>Rome;</hi> and alſo ſuper-ghoſtlie skill to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of ſpirits, whereby to profit ſpiritually their childe more then all the church beſides: and that by their meanes it was, that we had here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> the benefit of the laſt yeeres generall <hi>Iubilie,</hi> which (by their leaues) euerie Parſon of a pariſh might for the going for haue obtained, ſo indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent a mother is the Catholicke church euer, but eſpeciallie at ſuch a time: briefe, that the lawes of the land ſtand more penall againſt them, then all other Prieſts or Catholicks beſides (which is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true:)
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:178002:42"/> and that generallie they are the moſt enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and hated members of Chriſts militant ſpouſe both of the Diuell, the Turke, and the Hereticke, then all religious orders beſides; yea, or then the Pope himſelfe. All this and a great deale more to this effect like mounte-banks they tell, or cauſe to be told the ghoſtlie Conny aforehand, whereby to indeere themſelues vnto him, and perſwade him that <hi>quicum eis non colligit, ſpargit:</hi> and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion they will him therefore, that how long time ſoeuer hee was a Catholicke before, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare him now to a general confeſſion (yea rebap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme if they durſt) whereby to proſper the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnder their new lore.</p>
            <p>This introduction made (prouided alwaies that the Connie thus caught be a good Mammo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt, for a Ieſuite is ſuch a leach, that without Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in the vaine hee will not eaſilie faſten) then coape they, &amp; ſo next haue at all. Then (loe) fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth firſt a ſpirituall exerciſe, commendable (out of doubt) in it ſelfe if it be not abuſed, but the Ieſuits abuſe it all to lucre, poſſeſſing the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent whiles lie is in it, with ſo many ſcruples for his life paſt and alſo to come, that he muſt thinke himſelfe ſo verie a worme (or rather ſo verie a foole) as not worthie to vſe his owne, but to put all ouer as well what hee hath, as what hee is, to him his ghoſtlie father; ſeeing that both being &amp; hauing (quoth he) all is but to be a ſaued ſoule, which to obtaine what ſoule would not giue a whole world? For, <hi>quam commutationem faciet quis pro anima ſua?</hi> And, <hi>quid proderit homini to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:178002:42"/> mundum lucrari, animae autem ſuae detrim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nlum facere?</hi> And therefore (marke the end) <hi>vade ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de omnia</hi> (quoth he) <hi>&amp; da patribus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With theſe gulleries (I meane as they vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) my Ieſuit makes himſelfe ſole Steward (and that vnaccountant) of all his ghoſtlie childes both ſoule and ſubſtance, and him a verie childe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; ſo cunning warriners they are aboue all that euer I knew: for, whereas all other warriners vſe to catch the Conie with the purſe-net, they for their parts catch the purſe with the Conie, whereby they are both purſe and coney-catchers all in one. Is not this their making vſe of mens conſciences whollie to their own intereſts, like the Ape which being liquoriſh of a Cheſ-nut in the fire, tooke a Chit that lay there by a ſleep, and with his foot rakte it out of the embers, and all to ſaue his owne from burning, and to ſeeme to doe it mannerlie? Or rather is not this a caſting men into a trance, &amp; then a flat cutting off their heads? How manie men of worth and wealth haue they drawn into their ſociety by this guile? or wrought to be their benefactors to their vtter vndoings, not ſeeking to be acquainted with any but for their own turnes? How manie in this la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly widowes, &amp; wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-kind haue they thus fetcht-vnder, aſſuming vpon them all their eſtates; the letting and ſetting of their lands; the paying of debts and ſeruants wages; the marketting, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding euen of Chriſtmaſſe-capons, and what not, al but <hi>pios vſus?</hi> weening it pleaſant and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable in them (though religious) to be ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie worldlings what in their lay-child they hold
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:178002:43"/> an incumber. But this (coſin) is not yet (you may thanke God) their caſe with you, for that your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is liuing. Neuertheleſſe how they vſe him in this kinde, with more then licking their owne fingers, you may ſee before your eyes. You may ſee, and I haue heard you tell, both what decaie hath beene in your fathers eſtate, and alſo what factions in his houſe euer ſince (you know) who came thither, which before time were not. Yet neither your father nor you can finde, or at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe will not mend the amiſſe. The truth is that a Ieſuit is <hi>Piſcator,</hi> but not like S. <hi>Peter Animarum</hi> ſo much as <hi>Pecuniarum;</hi> and therefore his fiſhing is euer beſt in a troubled water. And this is the reaſon that whereſoeuer he comes he troubles al, being cleane oppoſite to <hi>Antelmus</hi> a Sea-ſpirit, who neuer ſhowes himſelfe but after a ſtorme, and they euer bring ſtormes with them; ſo as for their ſakes the note of the Church, <hi>Benedictus</hi> may well be chaunged into <hi>maledictus qui venit in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine domini,</hi> not onlie in <hi>England,</hi> but throughout all chriſtendome. For, runne ye ouer all the ſame, and finde mee the citie, the village, the houſe, where they are either manie, or anie, but there is alſo faction. In cities, with all the religious there; in villages, with the vicar, or cunſtable; in houſes, your fathers (as is ſaid) for example. Looke into our Seminaries, and you ſhall finde how peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able that of <hi>Rhemes</hi> euer was for not being vnder Ieſuits, how fruitfull of Saints, &amp; excellent men: and on the other ſide that of <hi>Rome</hi> vnder their Rectorate, how neuer without faction, and leſſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:178002:43"/> fertile of ſuch honours to our Church, or rather fertile of falſe brothers and Apoſtataes; and ſo likewiſe that of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They haue ſo manie querks and quiddits wherewith to make bate, and abuſe religion for their profit and pleaſure, that it is verie Puritaniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to tell. And for I ſpeake of Puritaniſme; haue you not (I pray) heard how not long agoe a Ieſuit here in <hi>London</hi> erected a kinde of familie of loue, lecturing by night three or foure nights together to his auditors al women, and thoſe faire ones for the moſt part? haue you not heard the manner of the night-meetings for feare (forſooth) of the perſecution by day, <hi>&amp; daemonij meridiani?</hi> &amp; yet al the day time nothing but reuell &amp; feaſt? At leaſt (I am ſure) you haue heard of manie, and doe know ſome, who miſſing their wiues the while, haue ſcracht their heads where it icht not, and bit their lips, and ſwore. Had ſuch exerciſe bin by day as in <hi>Puzzo bianco</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> it had beene well; but the nightnes of it, and that night by night, three or foure nights together, &amp; as manie dayes, oh (by your leaue) that ſmackes to too Corniſh. But this was ſoone diſcouered, and as ſoone ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, though much (I dare ſay) againſt the Ieſuit his loue rather then his charitie, and alſo without anie checke at all to him therefore to this day, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from his Prouinciall, or the Arch-prieſt that euer we heard of.</p>
            <p>As often as I thinke of this occurrent here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, applying it to their eaſie liuing throughout all chriſtendome beſides; me thinkes
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:178002:44"/> that not father <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> but ſome <hi>Pompo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Latus,</hi> or <hi>Macharonicus Festus</hi> ſhould haue beene their Founder; or that they are deſcended of the <hi>Fratricelli</hi> thoſe Lumbard-Libertines, with onlie their name chaunged into <hi>Patricelli:</hi> and yet for al that, the good men are partlie to be excuſed too conſidering their wealth, though not excuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for their wealth. For, omitting what is freely giuen them, if their conſciences be to gather it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waies, and in other countries as it is in ours, I doe not ſee what vow they need greatlie to make of Pouertie. For, ſay that a man giue them a thouſand pounds in <hi>Pios vſus</hi> to be diſtributed by their hand; if it be with the addition <hi>proprios,</hi> then there is no queſtion but they are honeſtlie worth a thouſand pounds at a clap: but ſay <hi>alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos,</hi> and name yee with-all what <hi>alienos;</hi> yet in this caſe too they make it theirs, by conſtruing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues <hi>veriſsimè alienos</hi> afore all others, as (trulie) ſuch they are here in <hi>England (viz)</hi> aliens from all Engliſh-nature, Spaniſh-aliens, aliens to all that is called Engliſh ſaue onlie Engliſh monie: for, ſo are they Denizens more then due or worthie, were it but for ſuch their coſoning-conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Againe, giue a Ieſuit ſuch another ſumme of monie in <hi>Pios vſus</hi> in the neuter gender, neyther expreſſing <hi>proprios,</hi> nor what <hi>alienos;</hi> that alſo they make their owne vpon this ground, that <hi>qui tacet conſentire videtur,</hi> and <hi>qui contra me non eſt mecum eſt.</hi> Thus gull they the religious minded toward them both quicke and dead; whiles on the other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide what vſe they make of ſuch In-comes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:178002:44"/> their <hi>Bancoes</hi> and ſtockes richlie going both here and beyond ſea, the preſent ſchiſme &amp; ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals in our Church moſt lamentablie declare.</p>
            <p>I pretermit in particular the large almes that dayly hath beene, and is giuen them here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (a point which belongs to that part of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmeticke which is called Multiplication) as firſt my Lord Burleighes-houſe in the Strand, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them by a gentleman dying beyond the ſeas, and pretending title to that plot: but this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath hath a reference to the conqueſt; &amp; good reaſon, for that (I doubt me) they will not in haſte wage that title againſt his Lordſhip in this time. Three hundred pounds a yeere of inheritance giuen them elſ-where; a hundred by another; a hundred markes in another place; &amp; ſo (I thinke) <hi>in infinitum,</hi> all conuayed ouer to them in vſes till the Conqueſt: in ſo much as with what is giuen them, and what they get beſides (for all is fiſh that comes to net with them, be it by excheate or cheating; as manie prankes of theirs I could diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer vnto you in that latter kind) I verily thinke their profits to amount yeerelie to halfe as much as the Queenes reuenue by Recuſants; ſo lucra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuelie they begin where the old clergie of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> left, and for which (together with the manie other ſcandals that proceeded from ſuch their riches) God hath hitherto as we ſee and feele, giuen ouer his Church and our country both, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauie hand of hereſie: though a great deale fouler and groſſer tranſgreſſe is this of theirs at this day, then that of the old clergie; it being in
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:178002:45"/> time of perſecution, and that in full fauour of the time. And yet for all this ſo great bountie of Catholicks vnto them, they are the vngratefulleſt perſons vnder heauen to their Benefactors, if they haue occaſion to vſe them, either here or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond ſea (as I haue knowne it by ſome) as not a Iew more. Nor euer was there more pouertie both in the Seminaries, and likewiſe in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons here at home, nor more faction ouer all then now, that they haue thus ingroſſed all charitie to themſelues. In which reſpect I could wiſh all Engliſh-Catholickes eſpeciallie my friends to be their owne Almoners, or els if they needes will doe it by the hand of a Ieſuit, that they beare as wel an eye ouer them, as a heart toward them, for (I aſſure them) they will elſe finde them-ſelues gull'd by their father-hoods dayly more &amp; more. I could alſo wiſh that good Capuchine whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, that ſhould happen to carrie a Ieſuit ouer a brooke, to examine and ſearch him well for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie afore he take him vp vpon his backe, leaſt hee breake his rule in carrying coyne about him, and be forc'd againſt the charitie that was in S. <hi>Fraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> to ſlip him downe (for ſauing his ſaide vow) into the ſtreame. Laſtlie, I could wiſh both the Lay and Clergie of our countrie to beware of all <hi>Zizaniaes</hi> amongſt them, publike or priuate; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and to come; and to looke well into the groundes of the ſame; in ſo doing it is ten to one but they ſhall finde either a Ieſuit, or a Ieſuited perſon at one end of the line, ſo well they loue to fiſh (as is ſaid) in puddle water, and frollicke in
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:178002:45"/> ſtormes, &amp; which is worſt of all, when they haue ſeru'd their turnes by anie, to laugh the partie to ſcorne be he ſtranger or their owne vowed Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement.</p>
            <p>Infinite is their practiſe in this kinde, and their inſtruments as manie; whom firſt they make to their hand, and trie throughlie before they vſe them. And that was the reaſon why that not long agoe, a Gentleman of good ſort my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, whom they would verie faine haue wrought theirs; vpon his not making a generall confeſſion to his new father the Ieſuit (as dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it impertinent though hee inſtantlie requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſame) what did the good father? forſooth, he tooke the confeſſion which he made, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued him; but yet to ſhew his diſguſt, brought him not the bleſſed Sacrament the next day as he promiſt, neither euer after came hee at him. Was this (I pray) religious dealing, or rather not moſt impious, ſo to ſeeke to diue into a mans conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whereby to diſcerne radicallie (as it were) in the Sacrament what mould hee was made of? whether apt to ſerue their ſeditious turnes or not, without that they neede to trouble themſelues with anie farther triall of the man then thus briefelie by the Sacrament, which of all other is the moſt ſincere? Could Machiauell himſelfe haue beene ſo prophane?</p>
            <p>If then they dare to diue ſo ſacrilegiouſlie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mens conſciences in the Sacraments to ſerue their lewd turnes, you may imagine how true the premiſſes are of their diuing into mens purſes to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:178002:46"/> the ſame end; and how much they would ſcorne to come an Ace behind either Machiauell or his Maiſter, in anie other paultrie whatſoeuer againſt either religion or moralitie. What wreſting of Scriptures, together with their conſciences to their preſent turnes? As for example, the libeller aſſeuers all Neutrals in whatſoeuer controuerſie, to be in the predicament of tranſgreſſors, yea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies; becauſe (ſaith he) <hi>Qui non eſt mecum, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra me eſt:</hi> and yet in almes-matters whereto anie of them are deputed diſtributors (as afore-ſaid) in the Neuter-gender, they interpret that neutra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie <hi>in bonam parte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (viz)</hi> as almes meant to them, as much to ſay as, <hi>Quod contra me non eſt, mecum eſt.</hi> And no meruaile if they deale ſo with the neuter, ſeeing that euen the expreſſe dole of the Teſtator <hi>(ad alios)</hi> they haue the conſcience to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate to themſelues, as is alſo aboue-ſaid. So likewiſe of Puneiſme, which in all honourable comparatiues is and euer was reputed a blemiſh, they interpret the Puneiſme of their Societie as an honour aboue the auncientie of all other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Orders in the church, euen as Mahomet did his law aboue either <hi>Moſes</hi> or Chriſts for being after them both, and none to come (ſay they) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it. Againe for Saints, which is a moſt ſweet and important point of chriſtian religion; they, becauſe they haue none as yet in the calendar of their Societie, you haue read aboue what they ſay. In like manner, whereas the Scripture de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth that man accurſed <hi>per quem ſcandalum venit,</hi> they in this their ſchiſme haue procured
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:178002:46"/> their Arch-prieſt to ſuſpend &amp;c. the Appealants to the holy-ſea touching the ſame; as though that ſchiſme were <hi>ex parte ſcandalum accipientis,</hi> and not <hi>dantis;</hi> and ſo by conſequence the curſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Appealants, and not to them. Briefe, they goe altogether by their owne grounds, and thoſe fram'd to their own priuate intereſts; which though they be in many matters meerelie againſt grace, or nature, or both; yet their conſtructions (forſooth) muſt allow them iuſt.</p>
            <p>Vpon this lawleſſe liberty, detraction which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt al not onlie chriſtians but heathen men, is &amp; euer was held a vice, is a neceſſarie vertue to be vſed oftentimes amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. As for example, in the preſent caſe of the Appeale, wherin they hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their rule ouer the Seminaries expedient and for the auaile of our Church, yee ſee how they maintaine their detractious libell againſt the withſtanders of ſuch their iuriſdiction, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe as many foule mouthes againſt them as they can, diſordring all our church.</p>
            <p>In like manner, their Poſition being that her Maieſtie is an heretike, and an excommunicated Princeſſe, and conſequentlie to be depoſed; what Ieſabeling of her haue I heard them vſe? what queſtioning whether yet no <hi>Iehu</hi> haue ſubdued her? whether yet not giuen ouer by God? why yet ſhe proſpereth? why yet ſhe raignes? why yet ſhee liues? what defaming her? what throwing ſoyle at her picture? what auowing her royall Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Floures de Luz, no better worth then to ſerue for ſignes to bawdie houſes? And not only
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:178002:47"/> doe the Ieſuits, and Ieſuited vſe her Maieſtie thus as in her royall and annointed perſon (as to my expreſſe knowledge in theſe particulars they haue done, and worſe, which for good manner I omit) but more, for her ſake how glad are they both abroad and here at home, when they heare of anie miſcarriage of our ſhips or men, by ſea or land (though in honeſt aduentures) and alſo how readie to blemiſh anie newes of our good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes by their lying alarums to the contrarie, and extenuations in fauour of the enimie? Are theſe men either Catholicks, or true Engliſh (trow ye) I need not ſay religious, that thus repine at anie (ſaie euils) that God permitteth to be done, but what they doe themſelues?</p>
            <p>In this kinde haue I my ſelfe beene bitten by them, and am to this daie, for hauing ſome nine yeeres ſince (as you know) deliuered vp to the hand of iuſtice (though vniuſticed) a certaine wretched fellow, who came in the nature of an Enginner, and in a Ieſuits name his ghoſtlie Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from beyond the ſeas, to perſwade my aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting his firing the Queenes nauie throughout <hi>England,</hi> againſt the next yeeres comming of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Spaniſh <hi>Armado</hi> which was pretended: how haue I beene euer ſince in their mouthes a relapſe, a ſpie, a treacher? All which, yea, anie of which I as much ſcorne to be, as I ſcorn ſuch their diſloyaltie and viperie. But are not theſe iollie mates the while, that thus a man to goe againſt their vnnaturall and graceles proiects in loyaltie to his Prince and countrie, is ſtraight to be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:178002:47"/> a ſpie, a treacher? So likewiſe, becauſe they thinke their Societie moſt perfect, and not nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding reformation, how haue they not mangled the good Cardinall <hi>Borrhomeo</hi> who held them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and was minded if hee had liued to haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected them all out of his Arch-dioceſe? How baſelie alſo haue they reprocht our excellent good Cardinall <hi>Allan</hi> with their defamatorie letters ſince his death, for his hauing the like opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of them, and making ſhew of a minde hee had if he had liued a while longer, to haue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne them from the Seminaries, both in the Colledges and in our countrie? Did not Doctor <hi>Haddocke</hi> (for example) their Votarie write thus fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Rome</hi> to his friend in <hi>Spaine,</hi> with the newes of his death? <hi>Benè profectò obijt Cardinalis noſter, qui ſi diutiùs vixiſſet, magnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſibi &amp; eccleſiae dedecus pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periſſet.</hi> Yea, euen the Holines of <hi>Xistus Quintus,</hi> they haue dar'd to depraue after his death, calling him in their letters <hi>Lupus,</hi> and I know not what worſe; and all becauſe hee meant if hee had liu'd but a few monthes longer, to haue reformed them. It is a ſhame that they haue no gagge put in their mouthes againſt ſo ſaucie libertie of lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, namelie againſt ſo excellent a Pope, and Cardinals as theſe were; whom as ſuch (to wit the Pope) euen a Proteſtant-ciuill author here in our countrie, hath in the latter end of his hiſtorie of <hi>Congo, ex profeſſo</hi> ſingularlie commended.</p>
            <p>Then for their lying, that is not to be greatlie marueiled at amongſt them, ſeeing it is the ſiſter of detraction. Doe they not herein euen at this
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:178002:48"/> inſtant notablie play their parts, in that finding themſelues now aſhamed of their libell, and the defence thereof hitherto againſt the Prieſts and the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Paris,</hi> and fearing the Appeale concerning the ſame likelie to light heauie vpon them ere long (it going on amaine toward <hi>Rome</hi> for all their braggard oppoſition) haue they not laboured, &amp; ſtill doe by all meanes poſſible, both braue and baſe, here at home and beyond the ſeas, and namelie of late to the Popes <hi>Nuncio</hi> in <hi>Flaunders,</hi> by procuring his letter to the Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants to perſwade them to a compremiſe, which muſt not be? and yet for all this doe they not in their vain-glorie giue out that (forſooth) the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealants are they that labour it at their hands, and that they refuſe? What impudent lying is this, &amp; other the like, which I could tell you of theirs, which to beleeue were neither Charitie, nor iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, no nor ſcant good manners? Fie, fie (coſin) I ſhould be aſhamed and wearie to tell you all their lying legierdemaines, &amp; diſhoneſt dealings which I know, and haue credibly heard of theirs, conſiſting of infinite querks &amp; quiddits; as men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall euaſions in their ſpeech, interpretatiue collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guings, halfe-fac'd tearmes, tergiuerſations, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue ſpeeches, whole and demie-dublings, the vulpecular-fawne, detraction with ſighes, buttes, and the ſhrugge, circular calumniations, holding it lawfull to be forſworne in to too manie caſes, intercepting, raſing, and forgerie of letters, and ſuch like; of all which they haue an Arte, and whereby they take away by ſuch what their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:178002:48"/> and what their example (being religious) not onlie all good religion from amongſt men, but alſo euen morall honeſtie.</p>
            <p>They haue likewiſe their Counſell of warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them like the Tentonicke-knights of yore, as appeares by their vndertakings for <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and otherwiſe, as is aboue ſhowne. Wherein their ground (I meane for <hi>England</hi>) being that this realme is not likelie to be wonne to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke religion by the word, at leaſt not ſo haſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie as behooues for their aduantages, do they not ſollicite daylie a Conqueſt thereof from <hi>Spaine?</hi> and alſo perſwade vs that it is both vtill and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable? It is (ſure) a ſaucie part in a religious perſon to be any waies a ſtickler betweene States be it for peace, eſpeciallie for warre it is a moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſeeming office in him, and ſuch as <hi>Iohn Gerſon</hi> neuer dream'd on in his imitation of Chriſt, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected as well to them as to all other religious; or if he had, they know his ſpirit too well in that point, though little they obſerue it eyther in that of anie other thing. In ſomuch as what for ſuch their ſoldiourlie mindes together with infinite their other ſcandals, the penal-Prophets ſaying, <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt praua in directa</hi> is falſe in them, but <hi>aſpera in vias planas</hi> aboundant true.</p>
            <p>For is it not a merrie life not to be tied to riſing vp to the Quire at midnight, but to lie a bed after the Sunne? to fare well, to be well clad, and all this <hi>ex profeſſo,</hi> not to faſt ſo much as Fridaies, to be a lier when they will, and yet be beleeued, a detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, a cheater, a courtier, a ſoldiour, a kil-Prince,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:178002:49"/> and what not? and all without controule, nay with allowance and commendation. Briefe, is it not a merrie life for a Ieſuite to trowle vp and downe the countrie from houſe to houſe, from good cheare to good cheare, in a gallant Coach, accompanied with gentle and faire women, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by neat ſeruingmen, his chamber to be deckt and perfum'd againſt his comming, yea, and a gentle-woman to plucke off his bootes by his iniunction (forſooth) for mortification-ſake? Oh monſtrous irreligion ſo to forget good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and ſo to make the Lay religious, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues Lay. What gallants would theſe men (trow yee) be in an indulgent time, that are ſuch vnder perſecution? Their quaint Prouinciall were he a gentle-man, might bluſh to read theſe imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſomuch moſt of them concerne himſelfe, the reſt his brethren. A ſweet reſt (beleeue me co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin) and yet ſuch as his poore vncle the Tayler at <hi>Lambeth</hi> fares nere a whit the better for. As for maiſter Arch-Prieſt himſelfe (whoſe reſt you may ſuppoſe is a great deale more, not in paternal Peuter but in pure ore) his brother the Peuterer is able to liue of himſelfe. And it is no maruell if the fathers, <hi>Gerard, Standiſh,</hi> and <hi>Liſter</hi> could not brooke to be impriſoned from ſuch pleaſures; the latter chooſing rather to be periured then ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued. So ſweet a reſt the Seminaries haue not; but a ſweeter (that is to ſay) Tiburne, and ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            <p>How truelie were the Seminaries <hi>in diebus illis</hi> afore euer Ieſuit was ioyned with them <hi>chara de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:178002:49"/> foboles, magni Ionis incrementum,</hi> and ſo are yet too a great part of them whom Ieſuitiſme hath not attainted; but then ſpeciallie when they were not to be ſaid in parts, but all one, <hi>anima vna,</hi> and <hi>opus vnum.</hi> Then did charitie flouriſh indeed as well in the Laytie as in the Cleargie, and hereſie loſe ground a pace; when both Catholicke faith and Catholicke life marcht together in ech againſt it. Then nere ſounded in our eares the tearmes, Schiſme, Rebellion, Suſpenſion, Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, Irregularitie, Faction, Appeale, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, &amp;c. All this came in with theſe Fathers, theſe Courtiers, theſe ſouldiers; vnworthie the name of Apoſtles, of Religious, of Ieſus. Grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe minded men, whom not the calamitie of a church vnder perſecution, nor ſhame nor feare of correction paſt and to come, much leſſe the lawes of charitie and humilitie can containe from ſo groſſe ſcandals, but needs they muſt be as bad, yea worſe vnto vs within our church, then our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon enimie is without. Pleaſe God, <hi>Catay</hi> or the <hi>Canibals</hi> countrie were their abode, rather then ſo ciuill a land as <hi>England;</hi> they being a farre fitter Societie to perſecute, then to be perſecuted, and rather to make Spaniſh ſouldiers of for the ſlaughter of thoſe heathen people vnder drum and enſigne, then to be imployed in Ieſus name for our church and countrie. And (trulie) I am perſwaded, that if as ſuch manner of men they might be ranſom'd from hence by our State as they happen to be apprehended (ſetting rounde ranſomes on their heads) it would ſooner rid
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:178002:50"/> them out of this land, then anie other courſe whatſoeuer, and help to bring home from their forraine <hi>Bancoes</hi> ſome part of our Engliſh-coyne againe, or at leaſt wiſe ſaue the reſt from their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
            <p>The Arch-prieſt was not aſhamed in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine abſurde letter of his to his Aſſiſtants, to tearme our reuerend Patriots the Appealants, <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom planè Eccleſiae noſtrae,</hi> wherein you may note the ſpirit of the man, how much it ods from Ieſus by being ſo Ieſuited. With how much more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon might theſe men retort thoſe tearmes vpon his owne and the Ieſuits vndeſerts, and notablie on Father <hi>Cowbucke,</hi> his, and with him all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes <hi>primum mouens?</hi> For the Arch-prieſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is in truth but <hi>motum mouens</hi> in the preſent Schiſme (to wit) betweene the ſaid <hi>Cowbucke</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Prouinciall-Ieſuit heere; betwixt whom, as betwixt two diſhes he is ſeru'd vp to our table for ſuch daintie as you ſee. This is that Arch which the Ieſuits haue made, or rather which makes the Ieſuits, and with them, way for the Spaniard to paſſe ouer into <hi>England</hi> if God defend not. This is our eccleſiaſticall-Triumni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate at this day, <hi>verè peſtis eccleſiae patriae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> noſtrae</hi> as they haue vſed the matter, and not the Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents thereunto.</p>
            <p>As for the firſt of them, beſides the diſparage of his birth and name afore touched, he is ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table a coward, that ſince his fugacie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſts Campe here, hee thought <hi>Paris</hi> too neere the broiles; for which cauſe, or whether for that his
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:178002:50"/> turbulent humour wanted employment there; he had not beene there long, but wiſhing to be farther off, &amp; rather ill occupied then vnoccupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (though the ſhort while hee tarried there hee wanted not his brabbles with ſome of his fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers in the colledge) hee made it a requeſt to his Rector to let him goe to <hi>Rome.</hi> Which his ſaid Superiour ſeeing no iuſt reaſon for, and thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on refuſing it him, marke the ſhift. Within a few dayes after, he tels the Rector how that by letters from <hi>England</hi> hee had receiued aduertiſement that our State had ſuborn'd, and expreſſely ſent ouer certain perſons thither to murder him how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer. And to make this good, he himſelfe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornes certaine Suresbies his ſpeciall votaries (whereof one I know) <hi>de facto</hi> to come one eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning late to their colledge-gate, with piſtols halfe in ſight and halfe out, and ſo with angrie lookes to aske to ſpeake with him. Which accordinglie was effected; whom the lay-brother the Porter o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening the gate vnto, and ſeeing in that ſuſpitious faſhion, came ſtraight vnto this reuerend perſon, and told him what he ſaw: who preſentlie taking him along with him to their Rector, with pale looke and trembling member, willed his ſaid bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to tel him what he ſaw: which the Rector vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and no whit ſuſpecting the packe by reaſon of his well fained feare the while, ſtraight credited his aforeſaid ſuggeſtion; and ſo to ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e his life, that verie night conuaid him priuilie out of the colledge with monie enough in his purſe; who on the morrow tooke his iournie toward
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:178002:51"/> 
               <hi>Rome,</hi> where within a few dayes after hee diu'd vp like a <hi>Dux</hi> all in Buffe, as though he had bin the greateſt champion in all our church. Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of theſe gulleries hath this <hi>Parſons</hi> brat plaid both before and ſince this pranke; but thus much for that.</p>
            <p>Perhaps you will obiect that this was before his Reſolutions: what of that? It was ſince he was a Ieſuit, &amp; true neuertheleſſe; euen as true as thoſe reſolutions were none of his owne but another mans collections, and he but the bare penner of them; for, had they beene his owne, hee would haue ſhew'd it in his life hitherto, or yet atleaſt, ſeeing that <hi>nunquam ſera eſt ad bonos mores via.</hi> But whether they were his owne or no, or but colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of another, and his onlie the penning; ſure I am, the man might haue bin much better occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied to haue continued his hand ſtill in that vaine though hee meant not to liue according; &amp; more credit it would haue beene both to him and his Societie, &amp; alſo more profit to our Church here, then his becomming ſince an eccleſiaſtical <hi>Steuk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,</hi> an Archprieſt-maker, and a King-munger. But ſoft, the king is not yet made; there is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Queene muſt be firſt askt leaue for that courſe in her Parke. Nor are the 40000. Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, no not ſo much as one (I truſt) nor (God willing) will euer be in ſo diſloyall addreſſe, as to entertaine the Catholike-king or his ſiſter on our ſhore, as this man hath ſuggeſted vnto them. Wherin he gulles them both, ſeeing that (thanks be to God) <hi>England</hi> hath as true Engliſh-Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:178002:51"/> in it, as it hath Catholicke-Engliſh. Nor e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhall (by Gods help) the Arch-prieſt with his conformable douſen make good that plot with al their braines.</p>
            <p>Let therefore father <hi>Cowbucke</hi> no longer abuſe the Spaniſh king with ſuch vaine hopes; neither yet make ſo daintie of his <hi>(Councell of Reformation)</hi> as he doth. See the doting man: hee hath fram'd an Eccleſiaſticall-<hi>Eutopia</hi> to himſelfe, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to he hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that title, the ſame to be exhibited at the next Parliament to be holden after the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt <hi>(viz.) Anno 1.</hi> of <hi>Phillip</hi> the third, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting that all Biſhops, Deanes, Prebends, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and generallie all the ſecular clergie of this land, muſt be Penſionary to the Popes Holineſſe: for which hee to haue a ſtanding reuenue and Exchecker here in <hi>England,</hi> out of which to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fray thoſe Penſions; the ſurpluſage (if anie be at the yeeres end) to be purſt vp to Saint <hi>Peter.</hi> And foure Ieſuits, with onelie two ſecular Prieſts of their chooſing, to be his Holineſſe Collectors of ſuch his reuenue throughout the land, and alſo the disburſers of thoſe Penſions. Hee hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, I know not what Aſſeſſements and in what manner, of all our Laytie toward this Exchec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker; in conſideration whereof, all Abbay-lands and other the old Church-lands of <hi>England,</hi> to bide as they doe to their preſent poſſeſſors, and the <hi>Peter</hi>-pence releas'd. Ouer &amp; aboue al this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenue to the ſea of <hi>Rome</hi> by aſſeſſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (as is ſaid) he alſo awardeth all deuotionarie-ſupplements to come to the ſame Exchecker, &amp; both the one
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:178002:52"/> and the other to paſſe through the aforeſaid Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors hands. This booke hee beares in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, as a moſt pretious iewell, and farre more charie he is of it, then the Dukes of <hi>Florence</hi> of their <hi>Tullie de Republica,</hi> which not all the world hath but they. Onelie once on a time to a verie deere friend of his, hee did communicate the ſame out of his ſight for a day; which day was a verie ſaucie day, ſeeing that from that day to this there hath beene a copie of it, and out of that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie ſundrie moe, which ere long (I ſuppoſe) will come forth in print, and (as I verilie thinke) long afore the Conqueſt. What for this and other his like fopperies, as procuring boyes hands of the Seminaries, yea, and womens for want of mens to the Ladie <hi>Infantaes</hi> title to the crowne of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and alſo to his Cardinalate, I do not ſee how a Cardinals hat will become the man, or how he hath deſerued ſo much as the linings thereof.</p>
            <p>I could therfore wiſh him (if he aime ſo high) to betake him to better buſineſſe then of State; namelie, to the penning of more Reſolutions like the firſt, which (trulie) was a good work, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter beſeeming a Parſon then a <hi>Parſons</hi> ſon; verie good (I ſay) whether it be good for him to be a Cardinall or no. For, though it be true, that <hi>qui Epiſcopatum deſiderat, bonum opus deſiderat,</hi> yet if he were trulie humble he would thinke himſelfe far vnfit for it, much more to be a Peere and pillar of the Church, as moſt men doe that know him rightlie, and better then hee knowes himſelfe. Had he continued ſtill in his Reſolutions, a man
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:178002:52"/> cannot tel what honour he might haue come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; for, that deſert was good, howſoeuer by his miſcariages ſince, he hath and daylie doth verifie the Spaniſh prouerbe true in him, that is, <hi>Come Santo, y caga Diabolo,</hi> as much to ſay, as: hee hath eaten downe Saints and voides forth Diuels.</p>
            <p>A man would haue thought that his diſgraced preſumptions in <hi>Oxford,</hi> where hee confeſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe macht, yea, and ouer-macht, would haue humbled him for euer, eſpeciallie being become ſince a Catholicke, nay and religious, and hauing taught others religious Reſolutions; that hee of all men would no more <hi>faoere aſcenſiones in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſuo</hi> (I meane ſo bad) but rather ſeeke to riſe by falling flatte downe (as it were) into his graue, knowing vpon what foundation the <hi>Babell</hi>-buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders became confuſed, and on the cleane contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie S. <hi>Paul</hi> rapt <hi>in tertium Caelum;</hi> and how in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciall it is part of the bleſſed virgin <hi>Maries</hi> ſong, that <hi>Deus exaltat humiles.</hi> If in the name of Ieſus this man haue not amended, but rather more and more offended, inuoluing all the Seminaries in his and his Societiſts vndeſerts in the opinion of our State, namelie, for trecherie againſt the State, whereby Gods Church hath bin and is the more perſecuted amongſt vs, and the good alike with the guiltie: if in proceſſe of ſuch his peeuiſh pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes hee hath ſought the liues of ſome excellent Prieſts his Opponents by ſleight and ſuborned treacherie, labouring to make his practiſes to be thought theirs: if he haue deluded the Sea-Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicke with falſe ſuggeſtions to the preiudice of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:178002:53"/> the Catholicke-cauſe, erecting by meanes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Ieſuitiſme amongſt vs, and a Spaniſh faction vnder an Arch-prieſt: Briefe, if hee haue beene a <hi>Iudas</hi> to Gods Church and his countrie, to the diſparage of the Seminaries and their Founder, whoſe Soules were ſincere to the good of ech: if he haue beene a fire-brand amongſt brothers to the diſiunction of their vnitie, and a great deale worſe, and all this in the name of Ieſus: no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile if he be a falſe-prophet in threatning ſome fourteene yeeres ſince, ones necke to be broken adowne the Alpes, in ſteed of a <hi>Viaticu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> which he ought to haue giuen him as out of the Popes Penſion, which the ſaid partie had through his fingring: but ſuch was his couetouſnes of S. <hi>Peters</hi> pence to his Holineſſes diſhonour; and withall he ſo lewd a Prophet. Farre ſweeter ſpirit had good Doctor <hi>Allan,</hi> being ſhortlie after called to the Cardinalate, who then and there (to wit at <hi>Rome</hi>) bliſt and rebliſt the ſaid partie againſt ſuch the baſtards malediction, and all other harmes; ſo as he yet liues to tell him hereof in deteſtation of his ſo malignant ſpirit. Laſtlie, if in the ſerene name of Ieſus, this man haue all this while bin ſo tempeſtuous a creature, it is no maruell if <hi>Cucullus non facit monachum.</hi> Rather is it to be maruelled why in that reſpect Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſhould ſay of late that S. <hi>Peters</hi> Court needes no <hi>Cuculla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos</hi> to grace it, more then togated Ieſuits, whereof hee himſelfe was once one. For which ſaying of his, I verily perſwade me, that wel may his Grace continue as he is a Cardinall, but neuer to ſee him
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:178002:53"/> higher, ſo improper, and too Ieſuiticall was that ſpeech of his. At leaſtwiſe I dare aſſure mee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to ſee father <hi>Cowbucke</hi> the one or the other, he being already high enough, to make his fal ſeeme ſo odious as it doth through his diſloyaltie and turbulence. Oh no, the Cardinalate is (queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe) an honor too high aboue his deſert, though inferiour to his heart; nay not onelie <hi>(ſupra)</hi> but alſo <hi>(praeter)</hi> thereunto: whereby I doe not ſee how it going one way, and he another (<hi>viz.</hi> hee doing all his deeds ſiniſterlie) that they can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiblie meete. His greateſt credit therefore will be, to ſay he went (beſide) it, or as the Fox did to the grape aboue his reach, to ſweare hee will none of it.</p>
            <p>And (ſure) it is enough for maiſter Arch-prieſt to be ſo dignified a man another day, who is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie come to his <hi>Dei gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia;</hi> which as well yee may applie to bare. <hi>Georgius Blackwellus,</hi> as to <hi>Archi-presbyter:</hi> ſo groſſelie the good man is miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken in his ſingularitie. It is enough (I ſay) for him to be a Cardinall, and be but for calling in of late ſo maieſticallie the Appealants bookes, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as (quoth he) the Popes Holineſſe hath not done it: which it is verie likelie if his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe had ſeene reaſon for, hee would either him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe haue done it, or willed him to doe it; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie his Holineſſe hauing ſeene the Latine booke (as he himſelfe confeſſeth) by his meanes. Again, and laſtlie, worthie to be a Cardinall, if it were but for his prompt acceptance of the Archprieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and maintaining by his ſaid authoritie, cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:178002:54"/> and decretaſs, ſo learned a tract as <hi>Listers</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his owne brethren, as yet he doth.</p>
            <p>But what ſhall I ſay of maiſter <hi>Lister</hi> himſelfe for the ſame? other then that he is verie worthie not of anie honour at all, but ſtill to abide as he is a Ieſuit till he repent and amend. What? a libeller and a periurde perſon too? that is <hi>pergo</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pero</hi> too faſt to perdition. Giuing his faith <hi>in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo Sacerdotis</hi> to be true priſoner to the Knight-Marſhall, and yet to breake that word, that oth, whereby to be the cauſe, that two reuerende Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries were that, or the next night apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and committed priſoners in his ſteed, was flat diſhoneſtie. But the good father perhaps had in taking that oth the moone his aſcendant, or ſome mentall euaſion wherewith to reſcue his ſoule at leaſt from remorſe, though not from the diuell if he broke it: (as for example) as hee was in that minde he would be true priſoner; or that for any thing the keeper ſhould know to the contrarie vntill he were eſcapt; or that hee meant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> runne away on his head, but on his feet, or that hee would not breake away ſo long as the knight Marſhall or his deputie ſtood by and lookt on; or that hee would not breake away as a Prieſt but as a Ieſuit; or that hee would not ſcape with a minde ouer to come againe with his will; or that <hi>nulla fides fernanda haereticis;</hi> or, oh how many <hi>ors</hi> might I make vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this point, ſeeing that as <hi>veritas vna eſt &amp; ſimplex,</hi> ſo is <hi>mendaciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> multifa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium;</hi> a large ſcope for a Ieſuit to ſcape away by from man, but not from God, &amp; but with ſhame
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:178002:54"/> enough. But what talke I of ſhame in him, who hath no grace? but rather (as I crediblie heare) is the man that ſtalkes vp and downe for all his ſcandall, as iocund as the fellow that burnd <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naes</hi> temple in <hi>Athens</hi> for ſame; or as <hi>Nero,</hi> who almoſt laught his heart out to ſee how hee had done the like to <hi>Rome.</hi> Were <hi>Attilius Regulus</hi> aliue, he would dart not onlie all the iro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nails of his tub at his head for ſuch his perfidiouſnes, but alſo his verie eyes. A ſhame that ſo a heathen ſouldier ſhould excel in the honor of his word, a religious Catholicke Prieſt though nere ſo lunaticke; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially he hauing ſince vſed his ſaid liberty ſo little <hi>in ordine ad deum,</hi> as to libell vpon moſt excellent men, and be a Schiſmaticke.</p>
            <p>A plainer minded Ieſuit a great deale was hee of the two (ſetting aſide his aboue-told night-works) who being (belike) ouer-buſied with cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable and cheating gettings, and therefore the leſſe able to attend his function of inditing Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, wrote ouer to Father <hi>Cowbucke</hi> to doe ſo much as to furniſh him with ſome Engliſh ones of his penning, aſſuring him that hee would conne them exactlie without booke, not doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting but that comming fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſpirit they would greatlie fructiſie his auditors, and be well applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. This was a letter from the beſt Ieſuit (I aſſure yee) at this day in <hi>England,</hi> in that he is a gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, though no wiſer then you ſee. The letter is yet exſtant, &amp; that in a Proteſtants hand, no whit (you may thinke) to his edification.</p>
            <p>As little is it to the edification of the hearers
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:178002:55"/> how Father <hi>Wartford</hi> (he that wrote the Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the mother Citie) told a verie friend of his a little afore his going ouer, how that he meant to become a Ieſuit, becauſe he could not brooke ſuch a one (naming the partie) to take place aboue him in the ſhire where hee remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, for onlie being a Ieſuit, and a man otherwiſe (he ſaid) of no deſert, but a verie dunſe. Was not this (I pray) to become a Ieſuit of frailtie, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then for more perfection that he hop'd to finde in being ſuch a father? I omit the baudie hereſie of father <hi>Edmonds (viz.)</hi> that <hi>Lupanaria Romae approbantur,</hi> ſo highlie to the reproch of the mother-Sea and Citie; for that both for it, and other his groſſe ſcandals, hee hath alreadie felt God miraculous reproofe from heauen in the eyes of a manie.</p>
            <p>I could thus in particular diſcouer vnto you much trumperie of the Society here in our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, but their preſent Schiſme may ſuffice for all: as alſo for that I ſhame to ſeeme ſo much the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit in detraction, though to Gods honour well it might be done, and (as I heare) ere long ſuch a ſubiect will come forth. For my owne part, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence the Inſtitution of the Societie, as autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed and commended for good and holie by our holie mother, and for hauing had manie good Schollers of it; being ſorrie that it digreſſeth ſo much from her initiall and fundamental honors. Not but that there haue beene ſome two or three of it, of good and reuerend deſert to our Church, though not altogether ſo to our countrie; their
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:178002:55"/> martyrdomes being to them as a <hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mium</hi> for the one, and (no doubt) a ſufficient <hi>Piaculum</hi> for the other: of whom one (being my neere kinſman) was ſo temperate in his opinion of this his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie, that in particular, my ſelfe queſtioning him on a time about the caſe and loftines thereof, and of her degenerating ſo from her originall by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too to ſecular, perſwading mee that it could not long laſt in the Church; his anſwere was: yet is it my comfort to thinke, that whiles it is yet ſomewhat aflote, my poore Barke may fleet away in her ſtreame to heauen: &amp; if hereafter through diſorder it doe ſinke more and more to a ſhallow, <hi>Ipſi viderint</hi> that come after. A right modeſt ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and importing plainelie (beſides what els hee told mee) that ſomewhat he ſaw in it which he himſelfe diſliked, and for which hee feard a ſhame comming toward it: and ſo likewiſe did old <hi>Iohn Haywood,</hi> when ſeeing his ſon <hi>Iaſpar</hi> now become a Ieſuit hee bleſt himſelfe, and ſaid vnto him though merrilie, yet in earneſt. <hi>Ieſu Iaſpar who made thee a Ieſuit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for theſe two or three Martyrs which haue bin to our Church of the Societie (which I think are all that haue bin in all this time of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution) there haue bin of it a father <hi>Cowbucke,</hi> who (as is ſhewd) ranne away moſt cowardlie from the like honour, and is at this day an arrant traytour to his Prince and countrie: Father <hi>Hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> who got himſelfe to be baniſht, giuing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the firſt preſident (if I miſtake not) to others of the like frailtie: and laſtlie, father <hi>Lister</hi> a libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:178002:56"/> and a ranke Schiſmatike, &amp;c. It is moſt ſtrange to ſee how this latter, but ſpeciallie <hi>Cowbucke,</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie men away with their impoſtures vnder the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of Religious and the colour of vertue; euen ſuch (a great manie) as what for their trauailes, and what for their reading, ſhould be both wiſer and more vertuous. How doe they extoll their flat euils before others vertues, and their notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wrongs before others notable innocence? As for women, their Sexes ordinarie frailtie excuſeth them; they hauing little or nothing beſides a will and a tongue. Amongſt whom how manie could I name vnto you both wiues and maids, who being aforetime modeſt, meeke, religious, charitable, yea verie Saints vnder the diſcipline of the Seminaries; are ſince their lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them, and deliuering their ſoules ouer into the hands of Ieſuits, become hautie, captious, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractious, factious, immodeſt, irreligious, &amp; what not? and yet for all this, with the Puritane are ſure to be ſaued. But for men, and ſuch as are or ought to be wiſe for hauing yeeres &amp; gray haires on their heads, and manie good meanes ſo to be, they (I ſay) to be ſtrooken ſo blinde with the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiticall planet, as to preferre ſo much a Ieſuits driuell before all the braines and ſoule of a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minarie, deſerues (certes) a motlie coate. What talke I of a motlie coate? ſeeing that God is iuſt, and euen his hand hath fallen heauie of late vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome of thoſe men, if not to the making them ere a whit the wiſer (through their extreme obdurance in their error) at leaſtwiſe to their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:178002:56"/> an exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple to others (leſſe foregone) to recant.</p>
            <p>I could name ye ſome of them, as for example; a kinſman of mine owne the great Executor of the North, &amp; as great a Perſecutor of the Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants in the Ieſuits behalfe, hath not God within little more (I take it) then one yeere, taken away firſt his wife, and next his onlie Sonne and heire, whereby his liuing is excheated out of his name amongſt his daughters, he neuertheleſſe continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as ſpleenatiue againſt the good men as euer to fore? It was no leſſe or little leſſe obdurance in wrong with the Ieſuits againſt the ſame par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in another kinſman of mine, who ought to loue the Seminaries better for the good Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals ſake their Founder, whom he ſometimes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and pretended to honour: as alſo to be more affiant in Gods prouidence toward innocence, he himſelfe not being foild in his fortunes at this day, for al he hath heretofore holden vp his hand at the Barre, and paſſed the pikes for the ſame; then to perſwade one of the Appealants (as lately hee did) that the Ieſuits being ſo mightie men as they are at <hi>Rome</hi> and euerie where, hee to let fall his Appeale, and ſo his honour and all. Thus get the Ieſuits al the coat-cards they can into their hands, weening thereby to out-face innocence that little Ace.</p>
            <p>I haue bluſht vnto my ſelfe for curteſie-ſake to heare the reaſons that ſome of theſe Gaudies (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my kinſmen) haue giuen for ſuch their Ieſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme againſt the Appealants; reaſons (inſooth) as were able to make a horſe breake his halter.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:178002:57"/> One ſaith, how that the Prieſt contradict autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and all good rule, which is as iuſt as Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines lips to the matter: another, that he ought not to read their bookes being prohibited by the Arch-prieſt, whereby neither to know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth of the caſe, otherwiſe then as his authority prompts it vnto them; ſo to agree with authoritie, though here ſo much to the preiudice of Prieſthood &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocents: another, that he heard a good Queene <hi>Marie</hi> Prieſt (being a man well nigh a hundred yeeres old, and ſo by intendment a dottard) ſay that (ſure) hee thought in his conſcience the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealants would fall ere long, and become flat he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks: a fourth, that their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>merce with heretiks in the proceſſe of this buſines is enough to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them and their cauſe: a fift, that Ieſuits are good Schollers and good men. Are not theſe and the like, ſweet reaſons (thinke yee) of men other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe very worſhipfull and worldie-wiſe, to be carried away with, from their true ſpirituall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? or rather is not Ieſuitiſme ſo very a witch?</p>
            <p>Briefe; all that is Ieſuiticall muſt be eſteemed rare, though nere ſo homelie: their verie Lay-brothers, Curſitors, <hi>Charlatagni</hi> and Apparators, muſt be all ſaid to be rare men; much more what proceeds from a Ieſuits owne pen (that is to ſay) from his profound, his religious, his acute, his ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refragable iudgement, muſt needs be double-oh rare: yee need not runne farre for examples. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Lister</hi> his treatie of Schiſme ſo fooliſh, ſo ſpitefull, ſo reprochfull to the Appealants, how haue they not hitherto, and yet doe be-rare it in
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:178002:57"/> deſpite of the mans moone? Alſo, how doe not other their bookes which I could name, and (I am ſure) you haue ſeene moſt toyiſh ſome, and treaſoniſh other ſome, paſſe currant &amp; applauded not onelie amongſt the vulgar, but (which is a ſhame) amongſt the vpper ſort of Catholickes. As for their Agents, I know and ſo do you, more then three or foure, who being men of no good tallent, faſhion, or deportment at all, but contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe rude, malapert, humorous, yea, and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt; are neuertheles accepted amongſt Ieſuited-Catholickes, for rare and ſingular men. The fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that hath a good ful mouth, to reſound them and their doings, and to calumniate their Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents (though otherwiſe a villaine) they eſteeme, and make eſtimable ouer all; yea, they make him their <hi>Entretenido de la Boca,</hi> that is, a kinde of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioner they haue, whom they call of the (mouth) which is a matter of ſome crumbs vnto the party: and generallie all their vaſſals of employment they haue a ninth Beatitude in ſtore for <hi>(viz.)</hi> that liuing vnder their beard, they receiue now and then a droppe of fat that falles from it.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, all other men, their doings and writings that ſmacke not of their Societie and Father-hoods (though otherwiſe excellent and of ſingular edification) they doe diſtaſte, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, yea and diſchace with manie a mocke, and manie a Flounders-mouth. Much more theyr ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Opponents, their perſons and pennes ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their detection (as namely theſe late prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bookes concerning the Appeale) no maruell
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:178002:58"/> if with all their kennell they lowdlie reproch, and Porcupine-like dart their quils againſt them. No maruell, if in ſuch their charitie &amp; good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, they aſſayed this other day by a forged let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter taken vp at the Clinke-gate, and deliuered to my Lord of <hi>London,</hi> importing matter of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace to a certaine reuerend perſon therein ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, and likewiſe to the ſuppoſed author there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (being ech their knowne Opponents) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to croſſe the good ſucceſſes of their ſeuerall futes then to his Lordſhip. In fewe, no maruell if reuiling, and ſlaundering men for not being of their Tribe, and within their circle; they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſe and denounce Gods heauie vengeance on their diſtaſters. How manie (euen ſome now Saints in heauen) haue they threatned misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune vnto, as loſſe of friends and goods, ſicknes, lim-wracks, ſodaine death, yea and their ſoules e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall hazard, for either not being with them, or flat diſliking them. In ſomuch, as there is no miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance whatſoeuer ſo much as ordinarie, that hapneth to any ſuch; but ſtraight they right holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie attribute it to their not being Ieſuiticall: ſo hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriticall, or rather ſo magicall and their decepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>The comfort againſt which their ſo great ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our Catholicke-Laytie, is, that the Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries themſelues (whom indeed the miſchiefe chieflie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerneth as yet) begin now to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their eyes toward their brothers of the Appeale and their owne honours, taking the caſe aright, and ſubſcribing thereunto. Inſomuch as from but ſix
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:178002:58"/> or ſeauen of them (which were all that oppoſd in the beginning) they are now (God be thanked) growne to betweene ſix &amp; ſeauen ſcore; which (conſidering the great number of Neuters, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Ieſuits doe not truſt) we hold to be as great a partie as theirs at this preſent, expecting daylie more and more of thoſe Neuters to come in. God of his great goodnes daigne it ſo, that ſo the Ieſuits being left in the lurch like <hi>Aeſops</hi> Iay (ech bird plucking away his owne feather) and alone to themſelues in all their treacheries; they may ſee and be aſhamed of their ingratitude and inſolence againſt ſo louing friends as they, who to giue them vpper place, and honor in our Church and countrie, haue therein neglected their owne, and their good Founders the good Cardinal, but Gods moſt of all.</p>
            <p>A man would thinke that were not the cauſe Gods, his Church, and our countries, but meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie mans; that euen the deformitie of their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners againſt moralitie and nature, might alien af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections from them, as namelie, their extreame ingratitude to their friends and Benefactors, and tyrannie to their ſlaues. For example, certaine of the now Appealants then Priſoners in <hi>Wisbich,</hi> were the charitable men that trauaild to bring to light a certaine towneſ-man there, who had libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt a Ieſuit, and other Ieſuited Prieſts their fellow Priſoners in that Caſtle, which they perform'd to the condigne reproch of the partie and yet the Ieſuits neuertheleſſe, aſwell ſince as before, gaue out with great <hi>Empheſis,</hi> that thoſe
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:178002:59"/> men themſelues were the Libellers. A faire requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall (ſure) of curteſie, and right Ieſuiticall; farre ſhort, euen of that of the Foxe, who held it a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward good enough to the Crane for plucking the bone out of his throat, he not to haue bitte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off his head when he had it in his mouth. It had bin a <hi>decorum</hi> in them, to haue ſhewd them-ſelues thankful vnto ſuch the parties kind office (though but from the teeth outward) were it but for hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their loues ſuſpect toward them, as then they did, and now much more by reaſon of the Appeale. You may gueſſe by this how homelie they vſe their own drudges, and how manie flaps of Fox-tayles they haue in ſtore for their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices.</p>
            <p>Here wil I, end touching Ieſuits and Ieſuitiſme at this time, being more then time, though no leſſe then due what I haue here ſaid, and worſe might ſay of them and it; not doubting but one day, Engliſh Catholicks will be both wiſer to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and more charitable to their true ſpirituall Fathers of the Seminaries, then thus to wrong them for adulterate and intruding ones. Deere ought to be to vs the memories of <hi>Allane, Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, Bristoe, Martin, Stapleton, Vaux, Cope, Reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalds, &amp;c.</hi> all excellent Seminaries, beſides no leſſe worthie men of the ſame now liuing; all whom both quicke and dead, this libell and the Arch-prieſts partaking with the Ieſuits therein, concernes to diſparage vtterlie, to the honoring of a few ſeditious and new-fangled Sirs, which muſt not be; but better it were they were all as far
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:178002:59"/> as <hi>India</hi> from vs, there to take their fortunes, ſuch (I feare me) ere long, as befell the Templars for their like Libertiniſme from the ſacred ſea. It is now aboue twentie yeeres, ſince this Societie comming firſt into our countrie, it hath laine ſo long time like a tub, heauie vpon the graſſe-plot both of it and our Church, whereby manie an vglie Toade, Euet, Sow-worme, and other like venom-vermin haue bred vnder it, the graſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cleane withered away. High time therefore it is, that it be remoued hence to her out-landiſh place againe, wherby both thoſe vermin may ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther flie with it, or die here; &amp; freſh floures grow vp in the plot, ſuch as before time did, &amp; ſuch as the Seminaries haue beene all this while, and yet at this day are round about it. Nor let the Arch-prieſt in thoſe Fathers behalfes, anie longer bite his brothers and whine ouer them ſaying: what a Gods name aile theſe men? what lacke theſe men? what would theſe men haue? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere for them, and ſo doe all honeſt and true minded Catholickes; they aile their honours which the Ieſuits by libell depraue; they aile the Churches libertie and Hierarchie which they would preiudice and ſupplant; they aile the peace thereof which they haue diſordred; they aile the ſafetie and reputation of their Prince and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, which they haue betrayed. All this the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealants aile, this they lacke, and this they would haue; yea, this they will haue at the Ieſuits hands if God ſay Amen. Belike the Arch-prieſt thinkes he is at hot-cockles with his brethren like <hi>Pilates</hi>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:178002:60"/> ſouldiers, who blindfolding Chriſt after his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, ſtrooke him, ſaying: <hi>Dic, quis eſt qui te percuſsit.</hi> So he in theſe his interrogations, though the ods be, that Chriſt was ſo vſed after his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, and theſe afore; the dice throwne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his garment after his death, and vpon theſe mens afore trial; he ſo wrongd by ſouldiers, theſe by Ieſuits and annoynted Prieſts. Againe, the Iewes their ſaying of Chriſt, <hi>Si filius dei eſt, deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat de cruce:</hi> doth not his ſaying that their booke of Appeale to his Holineſſe could neuer haue come to his hands but by his meanes, ſound as much againſt their innocence, and their abilities to make good the ſame? Well, well, had the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its but halfe as iuſt matter againſt the Appealants, they would ſoone <hi>deſcendere de cruce; Rome</hi> ſhould ſoone haue it, and all chriſtendome ring of it, ſo expedite meanes they haue both of purſe &amp; poſt, whereas our good men muſt goe as they may, <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, peano,</hi> and beare their quips the while, as, what aile theſe men? what would theſe men haue? But as fluent as they are of their flouts, let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that ſoft fire makes ſweet malt, and <hi>fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra iacitur rete ante faciem pennatorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the laſt point now of your letter, where you ſay that theſe ſcandals in the clergie haue &amp; daily doe quarre (as it were) the conſciences, and quaile the conſtancies of the Lay Catholickes, euen to the manifeſt and manifold fall of a great manie out of the Church: it is true (coſin) as you ſay, namelie, of the Ieſuits Pupils, of whom ſome haue (indeed) of late giuen verie groſſe ſcandals
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:178002:60"/> in matter of Faith, which (I heare) ſhall ere long be publiſht <hi>in cautelam</hi> to others. But what? aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much is God honoured on the other ſide in the conſtancie of his friendes and thoſe that ſtand. Greatlie are thoſe ſoules to be pittied that come not into Chriſts fold; but more thoſe that go out, becauſe, who knowes the will of his maiſter, and leaues to doe it, <hi>multis vapulabit plagis:</hi> and great puſillanimitie it is, that but ſeeing a fray and not needing to be in it, a man to goe hang himſelfe. Oh no (coſin) let no ſcandall within the Church driue vs out of it, how euer it make men daintie to come in; but ſtill let vs ſticke to the grounds of our ſaluation, which in it and not els where are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible. Euer let vs know the pipe of our Paſtor, and follow it in all occurrents ouer downe and dale like good ſheepe, and in all affaires ſort our ſelues according thereunto. It was <hi>Dauids</hi> zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous prayer <hi>vt inhabitet in domo domini omnibus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ebus vitae ſuae;</hi> ſo ought it to be ours, yea, much more ours, drinking (as we doe) of the fore-fount of the rocke of life, and he but of the hinder: in which drink is no remorſe, for that it procures no ſurfet. Let vs amid the flouds of <hi>Babylon</hi> ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Sion,</hi> ſweet <hi>Sion</hi> here in earth, and her tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant ſiſter the high <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and ſooner for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get we our right hand, then the one or the other of them. At a word, God and his Church need none, but all need them: <hi>Omnes egemus gratia glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria dei,</hi> and but by the one we cannot attaine the other. For, <hi>Non habebit Deum Patrem, qui non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buerit Eccleſiam matrem.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:178002:61"/>
            <p>Here (my good coſin) I will end for this time, not doubting but if you communicate this my diſcourſe to anie Ieſuit, it will ſeeme ouer-long and vnſauorie vnto his Father-hood: but as for both Ieſuit and <hi>Spaine,</hi> I am at a point, hauing ſet vp my reſt vpon true-Catholicke &amp; Engliſh loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie. And as little hold I it misbeſeeming me (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lay and a ſouldier) to taxe a Ieſuit of diſhone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, eſpeciallie in the behalfe of the Catholicke-cauſe and my countrie; as for a Ieſuit (being reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious) to vſurpe ſo arrogantlie and contumeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlie vpon the ſecular Clergie, and be an Elboer betwixt States. Ill beſeemes it them to be ſuch, but ſpecially any man to be diſloyal to his Prince and countrie: but what will yee haue of <hi>Vbiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries,</hi> other the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſ-nature, or rather no nature at all, and all becauſe <hi>Vbiquitaries,</hi> and for neuer ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a head of their owne nation but of a ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ouer them, whereby to be directed Engliſhly. This is the reaſon that like thoſe yee call Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, they range lawleſſe ouer all, regarding ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prince nor people, friend nor ſtranger, grace nor nature, but onelie to ſerue their own turnes, and maintaine their owne common-wealth. Wherefore as a certaine Spaniſh gentleman to his kinſman (reprehending him of a hard-heart, for letting a Moore-ſlaue he had, goe ſo extreme bare and naked in the dead time of the winter, ſaying that it was a ſhame vnto him) anſwered; Paſſe he ouer the cold as he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; as for the ſhame ile ſhift well enough with it: the like is my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to all contradiction hereunto <hi>(viz.)</hi> paſſe
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:178002:61"/> the Ieſuits ouer, their blames, their ſcandals, their Schiſme, their treaſons both to God and my countrie, as well as they can, and as for this ſhame to me in the meane time ile abide it. Eaſilie can I iuſtifie my doing herein, as namelie, in that being a member of the Catholicke Church, and of my countrie, I ought (vnleſſe I would ſeeme a rotten and a periſhed one) to feele my part of any pricke or ſpraine that is to eyther of them; and alſo by how much to kill a Viper within dores, is a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deed then to kill one in the fields; ſuch as theſe Fathers are both within our Church, in which they haue ſtung almoſt to death our true Fathers of the Seminaries; and alſo in our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie our other deere home, which they labour to betray to <hi>Spaine.</hi> Wherein whatſoeuer I, or anie other haue ſaid or written, if the Ieſuits take it (as hypocritically they boaſt) rather for a Probate of their patience, then a iuſt detection of their guilt: much good may it doe their conſciences (I pray God) I, for my owne part no whit enuying ſuch their ſecuritie, but rather reſting verie well ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of my owne. And thus (my good coſin) if I haue hereby complyed ought to your auaile to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the right, as well as I haue with God &amp; my conſcience, toward the honour of good Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Allan</hi> and the Seminaries his bleſſed brood, namelie, the Appealants ſo innocent and yet ſo iniured men; and alſo of all our Church and countrie, againſt the impoſtures and diſloyaltie of the Fathers: I reſt a glad man, not doubting but that according to the Apoſtle, I haue all this
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:178002:62"/> while bin angrie and yet not ſinned; and alſo not doubting, but to finde this mite of mine with the poore widow <hi>(viz.)</hi> this <hi>depoſitum</hi> of my loue to you, and dutie to God, his Church, &amp; my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie in heauen another day. Verie heartilie fare yee well. London this laſt of Nouember. 1601.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>Post-ſcript.</head>
            <p>SInce the departure of the three B-ees onward into their exile, and defence againſt theſe Hornets, you haue heard (I dare ſay) of the fatall Auguries which haue beene blowne out of the Ieſuiticall-trunke after them (to wit) how that no ſooner ſhall they enter into <hi>Rome,</hi> but ſtraight they ſhal be clapt vp into the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, or ſent away to the Gallies: ſo much (belike) they haue wrought the king of Spaines Embaſſadour there, to their Spaniſh faction againſt theſe Opponents. But God bleſſe them from all their hazards by the way, and then as for <hi>Rome,</hi> we make no doubt but to find it iuſt. The Preſidents which they carrie with them concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all their buſines they will ingroſſe at <hi>Paris</hi> of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like record, that howſoeuer their perſons ſhould happen to miſcarrie by the way through Ieſuiticall treacherie; yet thoſe may ſerue for the next that will follow after. Neuertheleſſe, Bragge is a good dog on the Ieſuits ſide, or rather it is Ieſuitiſme it ſelfe; though much too blame to calumniate ſo S. <hi>Peters</hi> Bar of iniustice afore-hand. Is not this worſe (I pray) then to conuerſe with Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:178002:62"/> which is all they haue to make their maine ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestion of at <hi>Rome</hi> againſt the Appealants, for want of better matter? But giue we their illuminated father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods leaue to brag and br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue, and depraue, as hitherto they haue done, their matter being ſtarke naught, and whollie ſubſisting on ſuch ſupports. Full little know they (for all their illuminations) what grounds the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifs goe on, or what cards they carrie with them. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be not you (good coſin) ere a whit ſtaggard with ſuch Ieſuitiſme in the meane time, though nere ſo big-bon'd, for (no doubt) but you ſhall ſee ſhame the end of it, when vpon his Holineſſe hearing of the Caſe, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſt will ſtrike the ſtroke, whereby it is to be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted that both the Appealants ſhalbe reſtored to al their honours againe, and theſe Droanes quite heau'd out of our Engliſh hiue, and the Seminarie-Bees confirmed therein againſt all both Ieſuitiſme and Spaine for euer after, to the infinite comfort of all true Catholicks, and namelie all true Engliſh men. God of his great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes graunt it ſo, that no more we may behold this Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall and Ieſuiticall skurfe on the ſweet face of his Spouſe our holie mother, but as heretofore <hi>in eius lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine videamus lumen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Master <hi>W. W.</hi> his late treatie the Ieſuits perſwade the vulgar and all ſuch as dare not (through the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſts inhibition) read it, that it concernes the diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of all the Seminaries from the beginning, as well as of the Ieſuits; namelie, that none of them haue in all this time of Perſecution dyed expreſlie for Religion, but all for treaſon: which how contrarie it is both to the whole drift, and the very letter of the booke, all readers may perceiue. See, how ſtill they would inuolue the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:178002:63"/> in their guilt, and with what ſleight and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence they ſeeke to ſet them ſtill one againſt another: inſomuch, us one or two of the Appealants partie (though not Appealants) are thereby (I beare) vpon preſent tearmes to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>agger. But what loafe haue ye that will not crumble? and what may ſuch their frailtie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect at thoſe Fathers hands, then the Fox-taile flappes aforeſaid. God and their good Angell therefore be their guard againſt ſo wayward humour, and make them ſee that in ſo doing, well they may marre themſelues, but not the matter: and what ſhame it were for them to goe from whence ſo manie depart. To conclude then this briefe Apologie for <hi>(The Important reaſons)</hi> I ſay no more, and ſo may the ſincere Reader find it: then, oh ſlaunder, oh Ieſuit; or rather no ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Ieſuite.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All this diſcourſe is wholie ſubmitted to the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of holie Church.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults eſcaped.</head>
            <p>Fol 10. l. 13. read Complainants. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ol. 15. l. 9. read i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. fol. 11. l. 16. read then a blow at a brothers. fol. 45. l. 23. read (I meane. fol. 113. l. 3. read growne to.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Auſpicante Chriſto Eccleſia, Patriaeque ſalus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aduocant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Maria Eccleſia, Patriaeque ſalus.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:178002:63"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
